<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christianity maintained. Or a discouery of sundry doctrines tending to the ouerthrovve of Christian religion: contayned in the answere to a booke entituled, mercy and truth, or, charity maintayned by Catholiques</title>
            <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15509)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1053:03, 1302:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christianity maintained. Or a discouery of sundry doctrines tending to the ouerthrovve of Christian religion: contayned in the answere to a booke entituled, mercy and truth, or, charity maintayned by Catholiques</title>
                  <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 3-80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Permissu superiorum. 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed I.H. [i.e. Edward Knott, the name Matthew Wilson adopted in 1602 and kept for the rest of his life].</note>
                  <note>Printer and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Chillingworth, William.  The religion of Protestants a safe way to salvation.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of K4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 5149.</note>
                  <note>Identifed as STC 5149 on UMI microfilm, reel 1302.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1053 #3 (British Library copy), and at reel 1302 #4 (University of Dublin, Trinity College Library copy).</note>
                  <note>Title page marked and stained; some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Trinity College, University of Dublin. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chillingworth, William, 1602-1644. --  Religion of Protestants a safe way to salvation --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIANITY MAINTAINED. OR A Diſcouery of ſundry Doctrines ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Ouerthrovve of Chriſtian Religion: Contayned in the Anſwere to a Booke entituled, Mercy and Truth, <hi>or,</hi> Charity main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by Catholiques.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Bringing into captiuity all Vnderſtanding vnto the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt.</p>
               <bibl>2. Cor. 10.5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>What is more contrary to Fayth, then not to belieue any thing, to which Reaſon cannot reach?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Bernard. Epiſt. 190.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, CHARLES King of <hi>Great-Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Moſt Excellent Maieſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Preſumption vvere not eaſily excuſable <hi>(Moſt gracious Soueraigne)</hi> in fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Sanctuary of your Maieſty, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of this poore Treatiſe, if the great importance of the Cauſe, vvherof
<pb facs="tcp:2349:3"/>I vvrite, did not change my <hi>Feare</hi> into <hi>Hope,</hi> and raiſe vp my <hi>Hope</hi> as high as <hi>Confidence,</hi> that <hi>Chriſtianity Maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> by vvhat pen ſoeuer it be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, needeth not feare to find benigne acceptance from ſo Gracious and Great a King as you are; vvho glory more in that moſt Sacred name of being a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> then in that moſt ancient Stocke of Royall Progenitours, vvhich ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly adornes the Diademe of your Sacred Maieſty. For I do not in this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion pretend to act either the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue or Defenſiue part of any one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Religion, honoured vvith the Name of <hi>Christianity;</hi> but I only come in the generall Name of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, vvithout treating vvhether it be <hi>Latin</hi> or <hi>Greeke, Eaſt</hi> or <hi>VVeſt,</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or of <hi>Rome:</hi> and therefore I cannot deſpayre of being graciouſly admitted by your Maieſty.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Scope,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>orke,</hi> as I am ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is only to maintaine the authority
<pb facs="tcp:2349:3"/>of Holy Scripture, the Myſtery of the Bleſſed Trinity, the Deity of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour, the infallibility of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, the povver of his Miracles, the neceſſity of his Grace, and of the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Certainty of Chriſtian Fayth; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Aduerſary, vvho ſeeketh to turne the <hi>diuine beliefe</hi> of Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>humane Opinion:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pag. <hi>36.</hi> &amp; <hi>37.</hi> &amp; pag. <hi>112.</hi> n. <hi>154.</hi>
               </note> Who teacheth that our aſſurance of holy Scripture, &amp; of all the verityes contained therein, is but<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>probable,</hi> and <hi>credible;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſuch as may vvell be falſe: Who continually vrgeth,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 112. <hi>lin.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>that God,</hi> as ſure, <hi>as he is good,</hi> neither doth, nor can require of Chriſtians an <hi>infallible, and certainly vn-erring Beliefe</hi> of his vvord; That men, neither are bound, nor can belieue diuine Reuelations<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 330. <hi>lin.</hi> 13.25.33.</note> further then they are made apparent &amp; euident to them; and that it ſufficeth vnto Saluation <hi>to belieue the Goſpell</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pag. <hi>37.</hi> lin. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qu.</note> 
               <hi>as vve do other Stories;</hi> as much as vve do<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 327 <hi>n.</hi> 5. <hi>lin.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Ceſars Commentaries,</hi> or <hi>the Hi
<pb facs="tcp:2349:4"/>ſtory of Saluſt:</hi> Who proclaimes<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pag. 144. n. 31.</note> the Apoſtles, vvith the vvhole Church of their time, to haue erred in matters of fayth, euen after they had receiued the Holy Ghoſt; That after their Deaths,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pag. 292. infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; 293. Initio.</note> the vvhole Church vvas preſently infected vvith vniuerſall Errour; and that the vvhole Church of the<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 338. <hi>lin.</hi> 5.</note> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils may fall avvay into Infidelity: Who shutteth<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 292. <hi>&amp;</hi> 393.</note> the gates of <hi>Mercy</hi> againſt penitent ſinners: Finally vvho openeth an eaſy vvay for the deniall of all thoſe maine points of Chriſtianity aboue mentioned, as it vvill appeare in this enſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Vouchſafe therefore, <hi>Moſt gracious Soueraigne,</hi> to conſider hovv Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is impugned by ſome, euen in this your Kingdome, and the incouenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dangers thereof; and preuent both them, and ſuch others of the ſelfe ſame kind, as may grovv greater if they be not preuented, by your Zeale and Care. I cannot doubt, but that your
<pb facs="tcp:2349:4"/>Maieſty vvill do it euen for the Piety of the thing it ſelfe, though my Aduerſary (vvho yet pretends that he is vvholy of your Maieſties Religion) giues you a more particular offence, by departing from the very doctrines, vvhich you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue. For beſides diuers other ſingle differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, he neither allovves the <hi>Nine and thirty Articles,</hi> vvhich your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, in your Royall Declaration, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to containe the true Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> nor holds he the <hi>Succeſsion of Bishops</hi> to be neceſſary in Gods Church;<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>356.</hi> &amp; ſequ.</note> vvhich experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to tend expreſly to the confuſion of the ſaid <hi>Church,</hi> and deſtruction of <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though God hath made your Maieſty moſt happy, both in a Royall Conſort, of ſingular and rare endovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both of Body and Mind, &amp; vvith a plentifull and moſt hopefull Iſſue, (vvhich vvith my hart I begge may euen laſt to the very end of the vvorld)
<pb facs="tcp:2349:5"/>and vvith an Obedient &amp; Loyall Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and vvith povver both at land and ſea, and vvith times both of Plenty and Peace, vvhilſt almoſt all your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are in vvarre and vvant; yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vvill euer be more able, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish You in all theſe Felicityes, nor to auert all diſaſters from your <hi>Maieſty,</hi> then not to permit, that there be any conniuence at ſuch enormous Errours as theſe, vvhich partly openly, &amp; partly couertly, are vented againſt Chriſt our Lord, and all Chriſtian Fayth.</p>
            <p>The God of Heauen preſerue your Maieſty in all Health and Happineſſe, to his greateſt Glory, your Maieſtyes ovvne Felicity, and to the ioy &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all your Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt humble, and most obedient loyall ſubiect, I. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ONDER not <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> That I entitle this Little Treatiſe, <hi>Chriſtianity Maintained.</hi> I giue it that Name, becauſe that is the thing which I endeauour heer to make good, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one who ouerthrows <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> not by remote Principles, or strained Inferences, but by direct aſſertions, &amp; cleere deductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally flowing from diuers of his doctrines: which if it be made appeare, I cannot but hope, that all who take comfort in the glorious, and moſt happy name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> will giue me <hi>the right hands of fellowſhip</hi> in this Common Cauſe. Ancient Pacianus ſayes<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prou.</note> of euery orthodoxe belieuer, that <hi>Chriſtian is his name, Catholicke his Surname. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke</hi> cannot be conceiued without <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> But Christianity ſo long as it is maintained, wil afford ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principles of beliefe, which may direct men to find, that one <hi>Catholicke</hi> Church of Christians, by meanes whereof our <hi>Lord</hi> hath decreed to giue <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> Let ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither preiudice auert, nor priuat reſpects diuert the good Readers vnderstanding from weighing in an equal ballance that which is herce layd before it. God forbid any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2349:6"/>Christian ſhould exceed the deſper are folly of the Iewes, who would not depoſe their priuat quarells, euen while they were circled with a hostile army of <hi>Romans:</hi> or be loſse aduiſed then the Romans, who tooke occaſion to make peace at home, by the pronocations of the Enemy abroad, indging it wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be ſwayed with feare of greater euill, eſpecially when they could do it, vnder the honourable title of a <hi>Common</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Liu. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>good.</hi> In which reſpect, I lay aſde, and as it were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get at this preſent, the Surname of <hi>Catholicke,</hi> while my ſcope is to maintaine <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> But I must notwithſtanding by the way deſire thee, by example of this Man whoſe errours I vndertake to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that thou wilt be pleaſed, to reflect vpon the miſery into which they do bring themſelues, who forſaking in truth that glorious <hi>Surname,</hi> content themſelues with the only name of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For conſequently hauing lost the <hi>Guift,</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> of ſupernaturall and infuſed <hi>Fayth,</hi> which in their <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> they receaued, they lye ſo open to all manner of deceites, that though they be warned of them, they runne vnawares into them: becauſe not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or not esteeming and weighing the neceſsity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of a <hi>Guide,</hi> they follow the <hi>Eye</hi> of their owne <hi>Reaſon</hi> only, which is too ſhort-ſighted to preſerue them from falling into the manifold pitfalls, which lye on all ſides of Chriſtian Fayth, as we learne by all thoſe, who in all ages haue ſwarued from it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> This Man, as the world knowes, had warning abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, in a little Treatiſe called, <hi>The Direction,</hi> that he <hi>ſhould not goe a deſtructiue way tending to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Direct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. 4. per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>no leſſe then of Catholicke Doctrine.</hi> How little he hath obſerued it, will appeare by the enſuing diſcourſe, penned to the like intent, and to no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2349:6"/>other, then, I dare ſay, the <hi>Direction</hi> was, to wit, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, or rather now, to diſcouer <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> couertly cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into this Kingdome vnder the shrowde of <hi>Naturall Reaſon.</hi> The vanome of which Sect being still, as it ſeemes, growing, or as I may ſay, compounding, it is no wonder if the enemy of mankind doth vſe all his art to make that Treatiſe more and more odious, by which it began to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection falſified.</note> 
               <hi>3.</hi> For to what other purpoſe doth this man in his preface ſay, against all Truth, and againſt the word of the letter, that the Author of the <hi>Direction, faſtens the</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. n. 7.</note> 
               <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Atheiſme and Irreligion vpon all wiſe and gallant men that are not of our owne Religion:</hi> and this in a different letter, as the very words of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectour,</hi> who yet hath neither any ſuch words or ſenſe. And againe, that<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. n. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as the Samaritans ſaw in the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenances, that they meant to goe to Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſo you pretend it is euen legible in the forheads of thoſe men, that they (that is ſome Proteſtants of worth, and learning and auctority too) are euen go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nay making haſt to Rome:</hi> words ſet downe in a different letter, and in the ſame context with the other words of the <hi>Direction,</hi> which yet hath not any one ſuch word, or ſyllable. And the Author was farre from preſuming to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the intentions of thoſe perſons, with whom this man would make him odious.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> He neither commended, nor diſcommended, nor ſo much as conſidered their <hi>vicinity</hi> to vs. His purpoſe was to ſhew that for want of ſome <hi>publicke infallible Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> they could not poſsibly auoyd frequent variations, by which whether they fell to come neerer to vs, or to go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from vs, was not materiall to his purpoſe. Let altars be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2349:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2349:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2349:8"/>demoliſhed to morrow, let pictures be defaced, let all that is done be vndone; Theſe laſt alterations will prooue his intent as strongly as the others can, wherein they happen to agree with vs. For his ſcope being to diſcouer the impietyes of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and to preuent the hurt of ſoules by forewarning them of the danger; to this end he declared ſome of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for which this Sect diſperſeth it ſelfe, and is able to do it, by working vpon the minds of diuers Protestants. The chiefest he affirmed to be the want of a publicke infallible Iudge of Controuerſyes, without which they are left to their owne <hi>priuate</hi> ſpirît, or wit, and diſcourſe, which must of neceſsity bring forth a multitude of differences, alterca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and alterations, and end in <hi>Socinianiſme,</hi> the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſsence whereof is to reſolue <hi>Fayth into Opinion,</hi> or into euery mans owne <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi> Now to ſhew that for want of ſome liuing <hi>Guide,</hi> alterations in matters of <hi>Fayth</hi> and Religion must needes be frequent, he alle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſuch instances, as lay open to the knowledge, and euen to the eye of euery man, and might afford a more ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of what he intended to euince: Yet ſo, that (as I ſaid before) his Argument receaued strength, not from their comming neere to vs, but from their altering from themſelues. From thence to inferre, that they must intend Popery, becauſe they happen to agree with vs in ſome things or rather ſeeme to agree, but indeed differ; is iust as if one ſhould ſay: The first Protestants in England, intended to perſist in Papistry, euen when they purpoſed the contrary, yea euen when they did actually depart from vs: Becauſe (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) they were not ſo furious against euery particular do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Catholicks, as ſome others were. And I wonder how theſe men dare belieue the B. Trinity, and other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall mysteries of Christian Fayth, ſince they must by this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2349:8"/>meanes agree with Papists, and ſo may feare least them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues be in a way to Popery.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Others are apt to belieue on the contrarie ſide, that the <hi>Directour</hi> was ſo farre from hoping that Proteſtants would become Catholicks by theſe degrees, as that he rather feared it might be a cauſe of ſome temptation to Catholicks, and a ſetling of Protestancy more effectually then could haue been performed either by the feruour of Zelots, or feare of Death, or any other meanes. And therfore I make bold to ſay, that although we Catholicks, his Maiesties most humble and loyall ſubiects, should be most vnworthy and vngratefull creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, if we did not with deepest thankefulnes acknowledge our infinite obligation to the tender Clemency of our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne: Yet I may truly ſay (if ſuch a Truth may be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without offence) that by many degrees They are more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and vnthankefull, who are vnquiet, becauſe the most moderate, that is, the most powerfull meanes which can be thought of, are put in execution, for eſtablishing that which they pretend to deſire, I meane the Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; vnleſſe indeed they deſire Protestancy should perish, if it do not in all reſpects perfectly and punctually ſute with their humours. For it is a true ſaying; Moderate things may laſt, but no Violence can long endure.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> This then was the <hi>Directours</hi> intention, free from all malignity, and directed only to matters of Religion, and good of ſoules in the manner declared aboue. Which to be true, I haue heard him affirme most ſeriouſly by all that can be feared, or hoped for in the next life, for all eternity; and therefore he could not but be ſorry, that any writing of his was interpreted to an other meaning, of which if he had but once imagined his words to haue been capable, himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as hearing any plea of defenſe, would haue been
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2349:9"/>the firſt to haue ſentenced them to be deſtroyed, and all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of them to be forgotten. And he hopes that upon this ſincere declaration it will be belieued, that if he erred, it was against his owne intention, and not, <hi>a more erroris, ſed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore amoris</hi> (as Bleſſed <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>not by any loue to errour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>22.</hi> Cinit. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>but by an errour of loue,</hi> to the eternall good of ſoules, by preuenting the daunger of their falling into precipices of <hi>Socinian</hi> doctrines.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> But the foule Imputation wherewith, euen in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle Dedicatory to the Kings most Excel. Maiesty, this man is bold to calumniate the whole Order of Ieſuites, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent doubtleſſe to make the <hi>Directour,</hi> and his endeauours hatefull, (tearming it, <hi>that Order which enuenomes poiſon it ſelfe, and makes the Roman Religion more malignant and turbulent then otherwiſe it would be: whoſe very Rule and Doctrine obliges them to make all men, as much as lyes in them, ſubiects vnto Kings, &amp; ſeruants vnto Chriſt no further then it ſhall pleaſe the Pope</hi>) is a most virulent ſlaunder, and moſt vniust vntruth. For the cleering whereof, though we might content our ſelues either with his ignorance of our <hi>Order, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine;</hi> or with the guiltineſse of his owne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in regard, that probably he cannot chooſe but know, that the intent of them, and our proceedings, are nothing ſuch as he proclaymes them: yet I thought fit here to touch briefly ſome grounds, whereby his Maiesty chiefly, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may receaue ſatisfaction, that there is no ſuch thing in our <hi>Order, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as this man is pleaſed to cast vpon it.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> And first (in regard, by what he ſayth in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, of the <hi>fourth Vow</hi> which the Ieſuits make <hi>of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall obedience to the Pope, proper to their Order,</hi> it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2349:9"/>ſeemes, that which he doth vent in his Epiſtle Dedicatory, hath relation to that <hi>VOW</hi>) it is to be vnderſtood, that, that <hi>Fourth VOW</hi> is wholy <hi>circa Miſſiones, concerning Miſſions,</hi> in order to the help of ſoules,<note place="margin">Conſtit. part. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> L. C.</note> as the words of that <hi>Vow</hi> expreſsely ſpeake, and their <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> declare thus: <hi>Tota intentio huius Voti Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendi Summo Pontifici fuit, &amp; eſt circa Miſſiones, &amp; ſic intelligi oportet liter as Apoſtolicas, vbide hae Obedientia loquu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, in omnibus quae iufferit Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Pontifex, &amp; quocunq miferit &amp;c. The whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of this Vow to obey the Pope, was, &amp; is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Miſsions, and ſo the Apoſtolicall Letters are to be vnderſtood, where they ſpeake of this Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in all things which the Pope ſhall commaund, and whitherſoeuer he ſhall ſend &amp;c.</hi> As for their <hi>Rules</hi> in generall, they are confirmed by the ſame Authority, which confirmed the Rules of all Religions Orders, and there is nothing in them which is not moſt holy, and which hath not been accounted ſuch, euen by our Enemies: or if there be any thing to be found in them otherwiſe, let this man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it if be can. They are not ſo hard to come by, but that S. Paules Churchyard may of times afford them. <hi>Doctrine</hi> their Order approoues none but what is taught by other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Diuines, as hath been often demonstrated againſt ſuch as this man is. And therefore we hold our ſelues bound in all duety to be, and to profeſſe our ſelues to be, as loyall ſubiects to the ſoueraigne <hi>Maieſty of our King,</hi> as louing and tender towards his <hi>Sacred Perſon,</hi> as reſpectfull and dutifull to his <hi>Commaunds,</hi> as any other of his ſubiects of what profeſsion ſoeuer; and to be bound alſo to teach all other ſubiects, that the ſame ſubiection is due, not only <hi>for feare,</hi> but <hi>for Conſcience</hi> alſo, by the law of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2349:10"/>and <hi>of Nations.</hi> This we ſhall be ready to make good at all times; as alſo to giue his <hi>Maieſty</hi> full ſatisfaction, by what meanes his <hi>Maieſty</hi> shall be pleaſed to appoint, in any particular point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>Practiſe,</hi> which is, or may be imputed to our <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> It were ouer great boldneſse to appeale in this to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing teſtimony of him, who in his experience abroad hath beene acquainted with more <hi>Communities</hi> of our <hi>Order,</hi> then this man hath beene with <hi>Perſons</hi> in his late chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges when he profeſſed himſelfe a <hi>Roman Catholicke,</hi> and conuerſed with diuers of vs: And by the equall hand which he carryeth towards all ſorts of perſons, obligeth all without preiudice to any. His Maiesty may be pleaſed to vſe what meanes in his Royall wiſedome he ſhall thinke best. And if he ſhould thinke it fit to pitch vpon ſuch a Testimony, we should eſteeme our ſelues happy in the choyce; notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that <hi>M. Chillingworth</hi> may conceaue otherwiſe, in regard that he wilneeds haue it, that <hi>Signor Con</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the Directour from writing bookes any more,<note place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> or at leaſt, <hi>hath reaſon to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> But he muſt know, that we are of a different diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and therefore though that Perſon were not of that eminent Integrity, Piety, wiſedome, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and all kind of worth as he is, who by ſo many wayes hath obliged many great Perſons to our nation, and howerly receiues a moſt gracious regard from thoſe whoſe iudgment and example all ſhould dread, we esteeme it a great happineſse to be ſubiect to all lawfull Auctorities. And whatſoeuer our skill be in Logicke, yet by Gods grace we will alwayes in hart, word, and deed maintaine theſe to be good and lawfull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: A Perſon of ſo eminent wiſedome as he is whom this man names, <hi>aduiſes</hi> me not to write; Therefore it is <hi>fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2349:10"/>for me not to write. And this other: A Perſon endued with Authority, <hi>commandes</hi> me not to write: Therefore it is not only <hi>fit,</hi> but <hi>neceſſary</hi> for me not to write. But this Logicke is no Philoſophy with <hi>Socinians,</hi> who will haue no Maisters' but themſelues, euen in matters concerning the eternall ſaluation of their ſoules, and will one day find to their cost, that Holy <hi>S Bernard</hi> vttered a most important Truth when he ſaid: <hi>Qui ſe ſibi Magiſtrum conſtituit, ſtul to ſe Diſcipulum ſubdit. He who will be his owne Maiſter, ſhall be ſcholler to a foole.</hi> But it is time for me to take vp &amp; conclude this Preface with this caueat, that I would not haue the Reader co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue that in this litle volume I haue touched all this mans Doctrines which tend to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but only ſuch as were most obuious. Nor is it my purpoſe at this time, exactly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute his grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds or anſwere his obiections, which may be done hereafter. My maine buſines is to demonstrate, that vnder the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he vndermines <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and ſetles <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſme.</hi> Which is the cauſe that mooued me to ſet forth this short Treatiſe for a preſent Antidote, till a larger anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were can be published. For who will aduenture vpon food if be know it is mixed, and euen incorporated with deadly poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? This is the ſcope of this Treatiſe, whereto I hope all Chriſtians will concurre. <hi>Socinians</hi> are but an aggregate of <hi>Iewes, Manicheans, Arians,</hi> and other condemned ſects, which all good <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to detest. I hartily with their Conuerſion: yet if they will obstinately reſist, in deſpite of their inuentions the words of the Apoſtle will be verified, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame alſo for euer.</hi> And they ſhall giue a fearefull account for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of al Churches, and errours against <hi>Chriſtian Fayth,</hi> when repentance will nothing auaile: Euen at that day, when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2349:11"/>as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> grauely ſayth:<note place="margin">Lib. 5. de fide c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Iew ſhall perforce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge whom he crucified; when the Manichean ſhall adore whom he belieued not to haue come in fleſh; when the Arian ſhall confeſſe him to be omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent whom he denied.</hi> And I may adde; when all good <hi>Chriſtians</hi> shall ioyfully behold him, whoſe <hi>Fayth</hi> they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to <hi>Maintaine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The Doctrines confuted in the enſuing Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe firſt Doctrine.</hi> That Fayth neceſſary to Saluation is not infallible. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>The grounds of this Doctrine lead to Atheiſme. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſecond Doctrine.</hi> That the aſſurance which we haue of Scriptures is but morall. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The third Doctrine.</hi> That the Apoſtles were not infallible in their Writings, but erred with the whole Church of their tyme. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fourth Doctrine,</hi> Iniurious to the miracles of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and of his Apoſtles. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The fifth Doctrine.</hi> By reſoluing Fayth into Reaſon, he deſtroyes the nature of Fayth, and Beliefe of all Chriſtian Verities. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſixt Doctrine,</hi> Deſtructiue of the Theologicall Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Chriſtian Hope, and Charity. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſeauenth Doctrine,</hi> Takes away the grounds of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Diſcourſe. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The eight Doctrine,</hi> Opens a way to deny the B. Trinity, and other high myſteries of Chriſtian Fayth. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ninth Doctrine,</hi> Layes grounds to be Conſtant in no Religion. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The tenth Doctrine,</hi> Prouides for the impunity, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of whatſoeuer damnable Errour againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fayth. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2349:11"/>
            <head>CHRISTIANITY MAINTAINED. OR The diſcouery of ſundry Doctrines tending to the Ouerthrow of Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt Doctrine.</hi> That Fayth neceſsary to Saluation is not Infallible.</head>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN <hi>Fayth</hi> being the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Hope,</hi> the eye of <hi>Charity,</hi> the leſſer light appointed for the night of this world, the <hi>Way</hi> to Heauen; if this <hi>Foundation</hi> be faulty, this <hi>Eye</hi> deceitfull, this <hi>Light</hi> an Eclypſe to it ſelfe, this <hi>way</hi> erroneous; our <hi>Hope, Charity, Light, Happineſse,</hi> and all <hi>Christianity</hi> muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2349:12"/>end,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</note> in worſe then nothing, in euerlaſting <hi>vnhappines.</hi> For as <hi>S. Thomas</hi> ſaid to our Sauiour,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Io.</hi> 14.5.</note> 
                  <hi>We know not whither thou goest, and how can we know the way?</hi> So what will it auaile vs to know <hi>whither we goe,</hi> if we follow a miſleading <hi>way,</hi> the Direction of a <hi>Fayth</hi> weake, waueriug, and ſubiect to Errour? ſuch is Chriſtian Fayth in this man's iudgment deliuered in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> with which I thought fit to begin, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it is the ſubſtance, and ſumme of that which he deliuers, and labours to prooue through his whole booke; and is perſuaded, that it is of great and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vſe, and demonſtrable by vnanſwerable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I muſt confeſſe, it is of great vſe to ground <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſme,</hi> which, as the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cap. 1. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Direction</hi> fortold, reiecteth <hi>infallible</hi> ſupernaturall infuſed <hi>Fayth</hi> from being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluation: and maketh our <hi>Christian Fayth</hi> of the Goſpell, and of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to be a meere <hi>human opinion,</hi> reſolued into the authority of men, of no greater certainty then other <hi>human Traditions and Histories</hi> knowne by report. Hence the ſaying in <hi>Charity Maintayned (that an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute certainty of Fayth is neceſsary to Saluation)</hi> he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xeth deeply as<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 328.</note> 
                  <hi>moſt pernicious and vncharitable;</hi> and els where<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pag. 325. n. 3.</note> as a <hi>great errour of daungerous &amp; perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conſequence;</hi> yea pag. 37. thus he writeth: <hi>Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſseſſed with this falſe principle</hi> (that Infallible Fayth is neceſſary) <hi>and that it is in vaine to belieue the Goſpell of Christ with ſuch a kind, or degree of aſſent as they yield to other matter of Tradition; and finding that their Fayth of it is to them indiſcernable from the beliefe they giue to the truth of other stories, are in daunger not to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2349:12"/>belieue at all &amp;c.</hi> It is true, that (pag. 36. n. 8.) he ſayth <hi>We cannot ordinarily haue any rationall and acquired aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, more then morall founded vpon credibilities,</hi> wherby ſome may conceiue, that beſides <hi>human and rationall Fayth,</hi> he ſuppoſes and requires <hi>Diuine Fayth,</hi> which is a pure, ſincere, firme adheſion to Gods word, not cauſed by reaſon and diſcourſe, but infuſed by the Holy Ghoſt's inſpiration into a belieuing ſoule. But in truth he diſclaimes from any <hi>neceſsity</hi> of Diuine Fayth, or any diuine light aboue the light of meere reaſon, and will haue men to be ſaued by the natiue forces of human, rationall, and fallible Fayth. <hi>Men</hi> (ſayth he)<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupra pa. 36. n. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>are vnreaſonable; God requires not any thing but reaſon; They pretend that heauenly things cannot be ſeene to any purpoſe, but by the midday-light: but God will be ſatisfyed, if we receiue any degree of Light which makes vs leaue</hi> the works of darkneſſes. <hi>They exact a certainty of Fayth aboue that of ſenſe and ſcience: God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires only that we belieue the concluſion, as the premiſses de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,</hi> wherof in rationall Fayth one is euer weake, credible, and not infallible. And againe pag. 112. n. 154. <hi>Neither God doth, nor man may require of vs, as our duety, to giue a greater aſsent to the mysteries of our Fayth, then the motiues of credibility</hi> (which are fallible) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue.</hi> This is his doctrine, which he deliuers often, &amp; makes vſe thereof to reiect the infallible Authority <hi>of Gods Church:</hi> ſo prophane, impious, &amp; vnchriſtian, as I wonder that a man profeſsing himſelfe a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, durſt venture to vent the ſame in print, in a Chriſtian country. For is the certainty of the Fayth which Chriſtians yield to the truth of the Goſpell, to the life of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Sauiour, to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2349:13"/>hiſtories of holy Scripture, of no greater <hi>diſcernable certainty,</hi> then the beliefe we yield to humane tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? I appeale to the conſcience of euery true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, whether he do not moſt cleerely diſcerne his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Truths of holy Scripture, to be ſuperiour, and incomparably more firme, then his beliefe of meere humane ſtoryes. That the Serpent ſpake vnto Eue, and perſuaded her to eat of the forbidden tree; that our firſt Parents were naked, and did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it till they had eaten of the forbidden apple; theſe ſtoryes &amp; other the like would any Chriſtian belieue them, yea would they not laugh at them, as they doe at <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables, were they not of more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with them, then <hi>Caeſars</hi> Commentaries, or <hi>Saluſts</hi> hiſtories, as this man<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 327. n. 5.</note> ſaith, they are not? That God requires not any thing of vs but only reaſon; That he exacts no more then that we belieue the miſteries of Chriſtian Fayth, with a human fallible aſſent; That diuine illumination aboue the reach of the light of reaſon is not neceſſary, that men may <hi>belieue</hi> as they ought, <hi>to pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>ſatisfy</hi> God; That God is ſatisfied with any degree of light, with the meere light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Reaſon, and with the weake and wauering Fayth, which reaſon ſtanding vpon probabilities can ground; Theſe be ſtrange and diſmall poſitions, and ſuch as ouerthrow Chriſtianity, as is euident by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons. I will point at a few.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Firſt it is againſt holy Scripture. <hi>Fayth,</hi> ſayth <hi>S. Paul, is the ſubſtance of things to be hoped for, the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things not appearing:</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Heb. M. v. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> or, as the tranſlation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in England hath it, <hi>the euidence, or ground, or confidence of things not ſeene.</hi> All which ſignify a firme,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2349:13"/>certaine, and as I may ſay <hi>ſubstantiall Fayth,</hi> much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from whatſoeuer aſſent, if it be only probable. For as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> diſputing againſt <hi>Abailardus</hi> (who likewiſe taught that <hi>Fayth</hi> was but <hi>Opinion</hi>) ſayth tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this definition of <hi>S. Paul</hi> (By the name of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> we are determined to ſome <hi>certaine</hi> and <hi>ſetled</hi> thing, &amp; <hi>Fayth</hi> is not <hi>Opinion</hi> but <hi>Certainty:</hi>) <hi>Audis</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epist.</hi> 190.</note> (ſayth this Saint) <hi>Substantiam? Non licet tibi in fide putare, vel diſputare pro libitu, non hac illac<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vagari per inania opinionum, per denia errorum. Substantiae nomine, aliquid tibi certum, fixum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praefigitur. Certis clauderis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, certis limitibus coarctaris. Non est enim fides aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſed certitudo. Doest thou heare the name of Substance? It is not lawfull for thee in Fayth to thinke or to diſpute at thy pleaſure, nor to wander hither and thither, through the emptines of opinions, or ſtraying errour. By the name of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, ſome certaine and ſetled thing is appointed thee. Thou art ſhut vp within certaine bounds, and confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in limits which are certaine. For Fayth is not an opinion but a certainty.</hi> This is alſo prooued by the words of the ſame Apoſtle:<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Although we, or an Angell from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen euangelize to you, beſide that which we haue euangelized to you: be he anathema:</hi> and where he ſayth,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb. 6. v. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>That by two things vnmooueable, whereby it is impoſsible for God to lye, we may haue a moſt strong comfort.</hi> For how can it be <hi>most strong</hi> if it be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded only vpon probabilities, as this man ſayth our <hi>Fayth</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> is? The falſhood whereof is yet further declared by the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Theſſal. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>When you had receiued of vs the word of the hearing of God, you receiued it not as the word of men, but (as it is indeed) the word of God.</hi> And <hi>S. Bernard Ep.</hi> 190. alleageth <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2349:14"/>in this manner. <hi>Scio cui credidi, &amp; certus ſum, cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat Apostolus</hi> (1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.) <hi>&amp; tu mihi ſubſibilas, Fides est aeſtimatio? tu mihi ambiguum garris, quo nihil est certius?</hi> But this Truth being certainly belieued by all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> it will be needleſſe to alleadge more texts of Scripture in confirmation of it. <hi>D. Potter</hi> (in whoſe behalfe you ſtept forth) doth euidently contradict your doctrine, when he teacheth<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pag. 143.</note> that the chiefe ground of <hi>Christian Fayth</hi> is <hi>diuine Reuelation,</hi> and that <hi>nothing but this can erect an act of ſupernaturall Fayth; which must be abſolutely vndoubted, and certaine, and that without this, Fayth is but opinion or perſuaſion, or at the most an acquired human beliefe.</hi> And Doctour Hooker (whom you alleadge pag. 325. for your opinion) in his Eccleſiaſticall Policy pag. 117. writes moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely in theſe words: <q>The greateſt aſſurance ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally with all men, is that we haue by plaine aſpect and intuitiue beholding &amp;c. Scripture with Chriſtian men being receiued as the word of God, that, for which we haue probable, yea that which we haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary reaſon for, yea that which we ſee with our eyes, is not thought ſo ſure, as that which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God teacheth, becauſe we hold, that his ſpeach reuealeth there what himſelf ſeeth, and therefore the ſtrongeſt proofe of all, and the moſt neceſſary aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto by vs, which doe thus receiue the Scripture, is the Scripture.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If we haue recourſe to reaſon, grounded on prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which no Chriſtian denyes, this doctrine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cannot be tolerated. For if a Chriſtian be not <hi>certaine</hi> that his beliefe is true, he may according to your owne confeſſion doubt, whether it be not falſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2349:14"/>According to your owne confeſsion, I ſay, ſeeing your ſelfe goe about to prooue<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 326. <hi>n.</hi> 4.</note> that Chriſtian Fayth cannot be abſolutly certaine; becauſe if it were ſo, it would follow, that any leaſt <hi>doubting</hi> though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and <hi>inuoluntary,</hi> would deſtroy it; which mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declares, that doubting can well conſiſt with that ſort of <hi>vncertaine</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Fayth</hi> which you goe about to vent. If once way be giuen for Chriſtians to fall vpon doubting of their Fayth, why may not they put themſelues vpon an examination in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and as doubting of the grounds thereof? And if this kind of examination be lawfull, who can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend an alteration, if they chance to find cauſe? as it is very poſſible they may, if their firſt aſſent was not infallible? How then could <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſo abſolutely ſay: Although we,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> or an Angell from Heauen ſhould euangelize to you, beſide that which we haue euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, be he <hi>anathema?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. But let vs goe a ſtep further. This Aſſertion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues way to belieue, that the contrary <hi>to Chriſtian Fayth</hi> retaines ſome probability, in regard that no high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of probability can of it ſelfe wholy deueſt the oppoſite part of all probability, this being excluded by <hi>certainty</hi> alone: Miſtake me not, as if I meant that the probability of one ſide were ſufficient to beſtow probability on the other. This only I ſay, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer belieues any point only with probability, hath in his vnderſtanding no preſent diſpoſition which of it ſelfe is repugnant to probability for the contrary ſide. And if Chriſtians muſt be of this diſpoſition in their beliefe, they can haue no ſetled or firme reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neuer to imbrace the contrary of that which for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2349:15"/>the preſent is their beliefe, which ought notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to be the reſolution of euery true Chriſtian belieuer.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This is not all. If we follow this doctrine, this other vnchriſtian Conſequence cannot be auoided: That one may be ſaued, though he belieue ſome ſect contrary to <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> as Iudaiſme, Turciſme, Paganiſme, or Atheiſme, with as great, or greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, then he belieues the articles of <hi>Christian Fayth.</hi> For proofe I need alleadg nothing beſide what your ſelfe ſuggeſt. In one place you tell vs, that<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pag. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>any fayth if it be but a graine of mustardſeed, if it worke by loue, shall certainly auaile with God, and be accepted of him.</hi> In another<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pag. 327.</note> you endeauour to prooue, that a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable perſuaſion, and <hi>hope of infinite and eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, prouided for all thoſe that obey Christ Ieſus, may be able to ſway our will to Obedience, and encounter with all thoſe temptations, which fleſh and bloud can ſuggeſt to auert vs from it.</hi> Ioine theſe two doctrines togeather, &amp; the iſſue will be; that any probable beliefe of Chriſtian verities, or euen of a God, muſt ſuffice to ſaluation, as enabling vs to <hi>worke by loue.</hi> Now it is cleere that your <hi>graine of mustardſeed,</hi> your <hi>any probable perſuaſion or hope,</hi> are verified in any low degree of probability of fayth in Chriſt, or God; and yet they do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude equal or greater probability in behalfe of the contrary part (for example that Chriſt is not the Sauiour of the world, or that there is not a God:) whence it followes that a man may attayne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though he belieue with equall or greater proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, that Chriſt is not the Sauiour of the world, or that there is not a God, then is that wherewith he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2349:15"/>the ſame, and all other myſteries of Chriſtian Fayth. Whether this tend not to Iudaiſme, Turciſme, Paganiſme, or Atheiſme, and to the ouerthrow of all Chriſtianity, I need not ſay.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Moreouer, who can oblige any vnderſtanding man, to dye for auerring the Truth of that Fayth, wherof he proclaymes himſelfe to haue no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? And you, O glorious Martyrs of Chriſt our Lord, did rather ſpill, then ſhed your bloud, if you were ſo prodigall therof, for a truth not certainly belieued to be ſuch. This is the very ſame argument, which melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous <hi>S. Bernard</hi> brings againſt <hi>Petrus Abailardus,</hi> a Progenitour of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who in thoſe dayes taught, that Chriſtian <hi>Fayth</hi> was but <hi>opinion,</hi> and not infallibly certaine:<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epist.</hi> 190.</note> 
                  <hi>Stulti ergo Martyres noſtri</hi> (ſayth this Saint) <hi>ſustinentes tam acerba propter incerta, nec du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes ſub dubio remunerationis proemio durum per exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diuturnum inire exilium. S. Paul</hi> ſayth,<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Scarce for a iuſt man doth any dye.</hi> And we may ſay, who will giue his life for a Truth? and moſt of all, who will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>giue</hi> his life, but thinke himſelfe <hi>bound</hi> vnder paine of eternall damnation to lay it downe in teſtimony of that, which for ought he certainly knowes, may prooue to be an vniuſt, and vntrue thing? Was the precious bloud of Chriſt our Lord, which by infinite degrees excelled that of Martyrs, ſhed in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for purchaſing probabilities? or for the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of Grace, to enable his ſeruants to dye for the truth of things, which in fine they eſteemed but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Far be it from the harts of Chriſtians to belieue, and their tongues to profeſſe, that a God of infinite
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2349:16"/>wiſedome and goodneſſe, would oblige himſelfe to reward men with euerlaſting happines, for imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the myſteries of Chriſtian Fayth, which may once proue falſe, and to adiudge men to endles tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for adhering to the contrary, which in the end may be found true, if Chriſtian Fayth can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be falſe, as falſe it may be, if it be but probable.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Neuer could any doctrine be offered to the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Adam more plauſible, then that our beliefe of Heauen and Hell is but an opinion in it ſelfe, and no way certayne, concerning things of another world; whereas worldly pleaſures, are in preſent poſſeſſion and certaine. If the greateſt certainty wherewith all Chriſtians hitherto haue belieued their fayth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, hath not byn able to ſtay the cariere of mens licenciouſneſſe; what ſhall we now expect, but, that flattered by this doctrine, they, who before did runne, will now fly, after the Idols of whatſoeuer may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to their ſoules or bodies, obiects of delight?</p>
               <p n="10">10. No leſſe liberty doth this doctrine affoard for belieuing, then it doth for liuing, giuing ſcope to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſyes, and endleſſe changes of Religions, as this man's fourefold alteration makes manifeſt, if all be true which is reported of him. In which inconſtancy notwithſtanding he ſeemes to glory, ſtiling it<note n="(r)" place="margin">Prefa. n. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>his Constancy in following that way to heauen, which for the preſent ſeemes to him the moſt probable.</hi> But of this more hereafter.</p>
               <p n="11">11. I will doe him the fauour to ſuppoſe that he holds no Religion more certainly true then that of Chriſtians, which yet to him being not certaine, what remaines in his perſuaſion and <hi>doctrine,</hi> but that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2349:16"/>for matters of fayth and Religion, God hath prouided no certainty on earth? which is not only of very ill conſequence, as I haue ſaid, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but expoſeth Chriſtian Religion to contempt among the enemies thereof, and disbelieuers of it: which this man it ſeemes doth not value a hayre; but meaſuring euery body by himſelfe, taxeth Chriſtians generally to be of the like weakenes, vngrounded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; vnſetlednes in their beliefe: <hi>For,</hi> ſayth<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pag. 327. n. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> he, <hi>men may talke their pleaſure of an abſolute &amp; most infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble certainty, but did men generally belieue, that obedience to Christ were the only way to preſent and eternall felicity, but as firmely and vndoubtedly, as that there is ſuch a Citty as Constantinople, but as much as Caeſars Commentaries or the history of Salust, I belieue the liues of moſt men both Papists and Protestants would be better then they are.</hi> I leaue the Cenſure of this Doctrine to others: I only note, firſt how poore a conceit this man himſelfe hath, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoureth to inſtill into others of the ground or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion, which Chriſtians vndoubtedly haue in their beliefe, making it no more ſolid or firme, then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of Caeſars Commentaries &amp;c. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that it may perchance be his fortune to be really forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to write any more bookes, if he can make no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſequences, then to conclude the want of <hi>Fayth,</hi> or <hi>firmeneſſe of Fayth</hi> in Chriſtians, from the faults in their liues, ſeeing there may be in a manner infinite other cauſes, why they do not liue, as they moſt fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely belieue they ſhould.</p>
               <p n="12">12. This therefore, you ſee is his <hi>doctrine</hi> concerning <hi>Christian Fayth;</hi> that it is weake, and weakely groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; that it is reſolued into the authority of men, as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2349:17"/>the beliefe of Conſtantinople,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</note> and Caeſars Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries; that a Chriſtian may really and deliberatly doubt of the points of his fayth, and yet be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (that is) faythfull. But that which doth moſt manifeſtly diſcouer the impiety of this doctrine, and of this his manner of arguing, is, that the reaſons by which he pretends to maintayne it, induce plaine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, that is, they conclude as well, that men can haue no certaine beliefe, knowledge, or aſſent that there is a God, or that we are <hi>certaine,</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian Fayth</hi> is euen ſo much as <hi>probable;</hi> which now I am going to ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The Grounds of this Doctrine leade to Atheiſme.</head>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Said in the former Chapter that if a Chriſtian be not certaine that his beliefe is true, he may according to this mans owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion doubt whether it be not falſe. I pleaded his Confeſſion, vpon an Argument of his which perhaps ſeemed to him a great ſubtilty, and hard to be anſwered, but is indeed a meere toye, and if it prooue any thing, it prooues the Title of this Chapter to be true. <hi>If,</hi> ſayth he<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 326.</note> 
                  <hi>this Doctrine,</hi> of the abſolute certainty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fayth <hi>were true, then ſeeing not any the leaſt doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting can conſist with a most infallible certainty, it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that euery least doubting in any matter of Fayth though reſisted and inuoluntary, is a damnable ſinne, abſolutly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structiue, ſo long as it laſts, of all true, and ſauing Fayth.</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2349:17"/>Doth not this Sophiſme tend alſo to prooue, that if one be tempted with <hi>inuoluntary</hi> doubts againſt the Truths I ſpake of, he muſt forfeit his <hi>certainty</hi> that there is a God, or that Chriſtian Fayth is <hi>certainly</hi> probable, and ſo either incurre damnation without his owne fault, which is impoſsible, or attaine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen without any certaine beliefe or knowledge that there is a God, or that Chriſtian Fayth is <hi>certainly</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the argument it ſelfe, it is of no moment. It doth not diſtinguiſh betwixt the <hi>Habit</hi> of Fayth, whereby Chriſtians are permanently denominated <hi>Faithfull,</hi> and which remaines euen when we are a ſleepe, and the <hi>Act</hi> or exerciſe thereof, which may be hindred by many good employments, as ſtudy or ſerious attention to any buſineſſe, without the leaſt preiudice to the <hi>Habit</hi> of which we are depriued on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Voluntary</hi> errours or doubts againſt it, not by thoſe which are <hi>inuoluntary</hi> and <hi>reſisted.</hi> If this anſwere giue not ſatisfaction, let him either afford a better againſt his owne obiection, or elſe profeſſe, that he doth not certainly belieue there is a God, or that he is not certaine, that Chriſtian Fayth and Religion is ſo much as <hi>probable.</hi> And by the way me thinks he ſhould reflect, that if he thinke <hi>euery Act</hi> deſtroyes the <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary habit,</hi> and in that reſpect no <hi>doubting</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the habit of infallible fayth, then the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Catholicke Diuines, that euery voluntary Act of Hereſy or Infidelity is deſtructiue of the habit of <hi>Fayth,</hi> ſhould not in reaſon and true conſequence be tearmed by him<note n="(v)" place="margin">Pag. 368.</note> 
                  <hi>a vaine and groundleſſe fancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. An other argument to prooue the fallibility of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2349:18"/>Chriſtian <hi>Fayth,</hi> in effect is this:<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 326.</note> We pray for the increaſe and ſtrengthning of our <hi>Fayth:</hi> Therefore our <hi>Fayth</hi> is not <hi>infallible.</hi> You might as well argue: We may pray for a high degree of happines in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: Therefore euery Saint in heauen is not perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly happy. Do you not know, that there may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of degrees, euen in qualities which haue no mixture of the contrary? No light includes darknes, yet one light may be greater then another. Thus the moſt imperfect acte of fayth, is <hi>moſt certaine</hi> in the moſt perfect <hi>kind</hi> of certainty, though not moſt <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> in the moſt perfect <hi>degree</hi> of certainty: and we may well belieue that the leaſt degree of <hi>Chriſtian Fayth</hi> is incompatible with any deliberate and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted doubt, or vncertainty, and yet pray for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe thereof. If you deny this, then tell me whether you may not pray for the increaſe of your beliefe of a God, and his Attributes, and for the ſtrengthning of it againſt all temptations (riſing either from the ſuggeſtions of the enemy, or from the weakeneſſe of mans vnderſtanding in order to ſo high miſteryes) as alſo of <hi>your certainty</hi> that Chriſtian Religion is probable in the higeſt degree of probability; and when you haue granted that you may, as I hope you will, then you will haue anſwered your owne argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnleſſe you will acknowledge your ſelfe not to be <hi>certaine</hi> that there is a God, or that Chriſtian Religion is probable.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A third reaſon wherby he endeauours to prooue that <hi>Christian Fayth</hi> is not abſolutely <hi>certaine,</hi> is this in ſubſtance: That ſeeing, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> aſſures vs,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pag. 326.</note> 
                  <hi>our Fayth is the victory which ouercomes the world;</hi> if our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2349:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fayth be a certaine infallible knowledge, our victory ouer the world muſt of neceſsity be perfect, and it ſhould be impoſſible for any true belieuer to commit any deliberate ſinne; How this doth follow I cannot perceiue, no more then one can inferre that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot commit as grieuous ſinnes as men that reiect Chriſtianity, becauſe the beliefe of Chriſtians is true, and the beliefe of others is falſe. The Angels in heauen and Adam in Paradiſe, were indued with infallible Fayth, yea and with Euidence, in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of diuers good Diuines; and yet the Angels and Adam ſinned deliberatly, and damnably. Fayth doth direct, but not neceſsitate the will, which ſtill remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning free, may chooſe good or euill. If he will ſtill maintayne the argument for good, then he muſt be conuinced to ſay, that he doth not with <hi>certainty</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue a God, or that vertue is to be imbraced, becauſe he can doubtleſſe commit deliberate ſinnes againſt God, and vertue.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Not vnlike to this is another reaſon,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> That <hi>Charity</hi> being the effect of <hi>Fayth,</hi> if our <hi>Fayth</hi> were perfect, <hi>Charity</hi> would be perfect, &amp; ſo no man could poſsibly make any progreſſe in it. Giue me leaue to ſpeake to your ſelfe; do you not ſee, that by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if you belieue in God with certainty, your loue of God muſt be perfect without poſsibility to make any progreſſe in it; which becauſe it is falſe, it muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, by force of your Argument, that you do not with certainty belieue a God. But as for the reaſon in it ſelfe, becauſe it concernes more then your ſelfe, I muſt tell you that it doth falſly ſuppoſe that <hi>Charity</hi> is both an immediate, and neceſſary effect of <hi>Fayth,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2349:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>without interuention of <hi>Freewill,</hi> which may refuſe to follow the direction of Fayth, and either wholy ceaſe to loue God, or loue him, now more, now leſſe. And therefore no wonder, if vpon a falſe ſuppoſall, that follow which is alſo falſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This is not a time to enter into long diſcourſes, how you confound <hi>certainty</hi> with <hi>perfection,</hi> as if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Fayth is abſolutely <hi>certaine,</hi> but yet <hi>obſcure,</hi> it muſt be alſo abſolutely <hi>perfect,</hi> which is a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, for it wants the perfection of <hi>euidence,</hi> &amp; hath a <hi>poſsibility</hi> annexed to it, that it may be both reſiſted, and reiected. But it will not be vnpleaſant notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor vntimely to ſtand a while, and ſee how exceſſiuely confident you are of the ſtrength and force of the foreſaid Arguments, and the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which you take in them. Thus you ſpeake of them:<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pag. 326. 327.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe you ſee are strange and portentous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and yet the deduction of them is cleere and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which ſhewes this doctrine of yours</hi> (you meane our doctrine of the infallibility of Chriſtian Fayth) <hi>which you would faine haue true, that there might be ſome neceſsity of your Churches infallibility, to be indeed plainly repugnant, not only to Truth, but euen to all Religion and piety, and fit for nothing but to make men negligent of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any progreſſe in Fayth, or Charity. And therefore I must intreat and adiure you, either to diſcouer vnto me (which I take God to witneſse I cannot perceiue) ſome fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy in my reaſons againſt it, or neuer hereafter open your mouth in defence of it.</hi> I anſwere, it ſeemes to me, that your <hi>reaſons</hi> are already ſufficiently prooued to be <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyes,</hi> ſince from them either nothing can be deduced for your purpoſe, or elſe you muſt acknowledge your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2349:19"/>ſelfe to haue no <hi>certainty</hi> that there is a God, that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is to be imbraced, or that Chriſtian Fayth is euen probable.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And yet I adde, that you muſt in another reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect alſo ſolue your owne obiections. Remember theſe your words:<note n="(zz)" place="margin">Pag. 36.37.</note> Yet all <hi>This I ſay not, as if I doubted that the ſpirit of God being implored by deuout, and humble prayer, and ſincere obedience, may and will by degrees ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his ſeruants higher, and giue them a certainty of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, beyond their certainty of euidence.</hi> And elswhere:<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 112.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods ſpirit if he pleaſe may work more, a certainty of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence beyond certainty of euidence.</hi> Now you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that theſe men may be tempted againſt their Fayth by <hi>inuoluntary doubting;</hi> that they may increaſe in it; that they may commit ſome deliberat ſinne; and may make daily progreſſe in Charity and good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, euen by the greater increaſe of their Fayth: and yet you graunt them a certainty of adherence, beyond their certainty of euidence. And ſo in this caſe your ſelfe muſt anſwere your owne arguments, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them to be but fallacies. Euen your maine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that Chriſtian <hi>Fayth</hi> can be endued with no ſtronger certainty then the probable motiues on which it relyes, by this ſelfe ſame inſtance is proued a <hi>Sopbiſme.</hi> For now you grant a <hi>certainty</hi> of Fayth not without probable arguments of credibility, yet not for them, it being more certaine then they are; and therefore you are ſtill put vpon a neceſsity of anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering your owne arguments. And whereas pag. 330. you make a ſhew of anſwering this particuler obiection, really you do not anſwere, but plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict your ſelf, labouring to prooue that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2349:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>that there ſhould be a certainty of adherence beyond the certainty of euidence, as the Reader may cleerly ſee, and ſhall be demonſtrated in due time.</p>
               <p n="8">8. One thing more I muſt not let paſſe, and it is, That whereas you ſay, We would fayne haue Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fayth belieued to be infallible, <hi>that there might be ſome neceſsity of our Churches infallibility;</hi> it ſeemes you are apt inough to yield infallibility to Gods Church, if once it be granted that Chriſtian Fayth is infallible. And with good reaſon. For ſeeing you teach that vniuerſall Tradition and other arguments of credibility, cannot produce an infallible beliefe of holy Scripture, and of the myſteries belieued by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; it muſt follow, that ſome other infallible mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes muſt be found out for the propounding to vs the holy Scriptures: which other infallible meanes euen according to your perſuaſion, being not Scripture it ſelfe, nor euery mans priuate ſpirit, there remaynes only the authority of the Catholicke Church, which as an inſtrument of the holy Ghoſt, may be an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble propounder both of Scripture and all diuine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. Wherein there is a large difference betweene the Church and other Iudges. Theſe in their ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or determinations intend not to deliuer points of <hi>infallible Fayth,</hi> as the Church muſt intend, and do it, if once it be granted, that from her we muſt receiue holy Scriptures, and belieue them with a certaine and <hi>infallible</hi> aſſent of Chriſtian <hi>Fayth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2349:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Doctrine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</note> That the aſſurance which we haue of Scriptures, is but morall.</head>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis man magnifies holy Scriptures in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, as the only thing on which he relyes his Saluation; but whoſoeuer ſhall walke along with him from place to place, &amp; marke well his wayes, will find that they lead to the quite contrary, and ſhew that he neither doth value them to their right worth, nor doth lay any other grounds, but ſuch as are more apt to breed diſeſteeme then eſteeme of them. This may be ſeene, in that he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth,<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 141. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62.</note> That our aſſurance that the Scripture hath been preſerued from any materiall alteration, and that any other booke of any profance writer is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, <hi>is of the ſame kind and condition, both morall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If this may be allowed, it muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the aſſurance which we haue of Scripture muſt in degree be much inferiour to the aſſurance which we haue of ſuch bookes of prophane Authors as haue a more full teſtimony and tradition of all ſorts of men, to wit, Atheiſts, Pagans, Iewes, Turkes &amp; Chriſtians; wheras the bookes holy Scripture, are either vnknowne, or impugned by all except
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2349:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; by ſome alſo who would beare of Chriſtians, and conſequently the morall aſſurance of them, and of the incorruptedneſſe of them, is the much the leſſe, and of leſſe morall credit. And by ſo ſame reaſon whoſoeuer builds vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this mans grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, cannot haue ſo great aſſurance that there was a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that he had diſciples, and much leſſe that he wrought wonderous things, and leſſe then this, that thoſe wonders were true miracles; as that there was a Coeſar, Alexander, Pompey &amp;c. or that they fought ſuch battailes, and the like. For theſe things deſcend to vs by a more vniuerſall tradition, then the former.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pag. 116.</note> Do not your ſelfe ſpeake thus? <hi>We haue as great reaſon to belieue there was ſuch a man as Henry the Eight King of England, as that Ieſus Chriſt ſuffered vnder Pontius Pilate.</hi> You ſhould haue ſaid; we haue greater reaſon to belieue it, if we conſult humane induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments only, and conſequently if Chriſtian Fayth be not abſolutely infallible, euen aboue the motiues of credibility, we are more certaine that there was a King <hi>Henry,</hi> then a <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> A thing which no true Chriſtian can heare without deteſtation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That which followes out of the ſame 116. page, is of the like nature, laying a ground for vn wary peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to reiect Scripture; For, hauing ſpoken of ſome barbarous Nations, that belieued the doctrine of Chriſt, and yet belieued not the Scripture to be the word of God,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pag. 116.</note> for they neuer heard of it, and <hi>Fayth comes by hearing;</hi> you adde theſe words: <hi>Neither doubt I, but if the bookes of Scripture had byn propoſed to them by the other parts of the Church where they had been before receiued, and had been doubted of, or euen reiected by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2349:21"/>barbarous nations, but still by the bare beliefe, and practiſe of Chriſtianity they might be ſaued, God requiring of vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of damnation, only to belieue the verities therein contained, and not the diuine authority of the bookes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are contained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If this be granted, why might not any Church haue reiected the Scriptures being propoſed by other parts of the Church? And why may not we do ſo at this day? Nay ſeeing <hi>de facto</hi> we know the verities of Chriſtian Fayth by Scripture only, according to your doctrine; we cannot be obliged to belieue the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe the verities therein contained are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be belieued, (for this very neceſsity you cannot belieue, but by belieuing aforehand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) but contrarily you may reiect the verities them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, if you be not preobliged to belieue the diuine authority of the bookes wherein they are contained.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Againe, you ſay that Scripture is the <hi>only Rule</hi> of Chriſtian Fayth,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Cap. 2 per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> yet it is not neceſſary to Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to belieue it <hi>to be a rule of Fayth, no nor to be the Word of God.</hi> The firſt part of this doctrine is the ſcope of your whole ſecond Chapter. The ſecond is taught purpoſely, and at large in the ſame Chapter<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pag. 116.</note> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 116. <hi>n.</hi> 159. Ioyne theſe two aſſertions, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion will be; That we are not obliged to receiue that which is the only ordinary meanes of attayning Chriſtian Fayth, namely the Scriptures. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ordinary way, we cannot be bound to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſtian Fayth, ſeeing it cannot be compaſſed without the meanes to attaine to it. For how can one be obliged to attayne an end, and yet be left free to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the only meanes of atchieuing that end? I am the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2349:22"/>freer to make this queſtion, becauſe you concurre with me in the anſwere, when you ſay:<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pag. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that God by his prouidence ſhould preſerue the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from any vndiſcernable corruption, in thoſe things which he would haue knowne; otherwiſe it is apparent it had not been his will that theſe things ſhould be knowne, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes of continuing the Knowledge of them being peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</hi> Now is it not in effect all one, whether the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture haue periſhed, or whether it be preſerued, if in the meane time we be not bound to belieue, that it is the Rule of Fayth, and word of God? Nay, ſeeing as things now ſtand we may find the verityes contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Scripture, ſufficiently expreſſed in innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other bookes, we may at this preſent in conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to your doctrine reiect all the holy Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting our ſelues with the contents thereof taken from other Authors, and not from the writers of the Bible.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Doctrine which he carryeth through his whole Booke, but particularly inſiſteth vpon in his third Chapter, that we cannot learne from Scripture it ſelfe that it is Canonicall, but only from Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, deliuering it from hand to hand, is no leſſe iniurious and derogatiue to holy Scripture then the former, ſpeaking of men in his ſenſe, that is, not as endued with any infallible aſsiſtance of the holy Ghoſt (which Catholicks belieue of the Church) but only as wiſe, or many men, or for the like human qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; for to this effect he ſayth:<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 72. <hi>n.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Tradition is a principle, not in Christianity, but in Reaſon, not praper to Chriſtians, but common to all men.</hi> This is certainly the right courſe to blaſt the Authority of holy Scripture,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2349:22"/>not to maintaine it. For beſides that which I haue touched already, that by this meanes we are not ſo certaine of Scripture, as of profane bookes, he muſt come at length to reſolue the beliefe of Scripture into the Tradition or Authority of Pagans, Iewes, Turkes, or condemned Hereticks, as well as of true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For ſeeing errours againſt fayth, or Hereſies cannot in his principles be diſcerned but by Scriptures; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be receaued, the teſtimony of one man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the admittance of them muſt weigh as much as of another, and be conſidered only as prooceeding from a number of men, be they faythfull or Infidels, true Chriſtians or condemned Hereticks.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And further according to the ſame principles he muſt acknowledge, that he belieueth ſome parts of Canonicall Scripture with a more firme aſſent, then others, to wit, as they haue been deliuered with more or leſſe generall conſent, or haue been more or leſſe once queſtioned: which is to depriue Canonical Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of all Authority. For if once we giue way to more or leſſe in the behalfe of Gods word, we ſhall end in nothing. And this hath the more force in this mans doctrine, who profeſſeth that the greateſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty which he hath of any part of Scripture, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſse of probability. What certainty then ſhall thoſe Scriptures haue, which participate of that probability in a leſse and leſse degree, according as they haue been deliuered with different tradition and conſent. How this doctrine will ſound in the eares of all true Chriſtians, I leaue to be conſidered, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelfe to oppoſe your Aſſertion with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>D. King,</hi> afterward Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2349:23"/>beginning of his <hi>first Lecture</hi> vpon <hi>Ionas,</hi> where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things he ſayes: <hi>Compariſons betwixt Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and Scripture are both odious and daungerous. The Apoſtles names are euenly placed in the writings of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foundation. With an vnpartiall reſpect haue the children of Christs family from time to time, receiued, reuerenced, &amp; imbraced the whole volume of Scriptures.</hi> You on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide ſpeake in a different ſtrayne and ſay thus:<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pag. 67. n. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>I may belieue euen thoſe questioned Bookes to haue been written by the Apostles, and to be Canonicall: but I cannot in reaſon belieue this of them ſo vndoubtedly, as of thoſe bookes which were neuer questioned.</hi> And elswhere: <hi>The Canon of Scripture,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pag. 69. n. 45.</note> as we receiue it, is built vpon vniuerſall Tradition. For we do not profeſſe our ſelues ſo abſolutly and vndoubtedly certaine, neither do we vrge others to be ſo, of thoſe Bookes which haue byn doubted, as of thoſe which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue.</hi> By this meanes what will become of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of <hi>S. Iames,</hi> the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and the <hi>Apocalyps of S. Iohn?</hi> And what part of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture hath not been queſtioned by ſome, and thoſe ſome ſo many, as would haue made vs doubt of the works of <hi>Tully</hi> or <hi>Liuy &amp;c.</hi> if they had affirmed them not to haue been written by ſuch Authours? And the only doubting of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> or ſome ſuch other about the workes of ſome Fathers, hath cauſed them to be queſtioned by diuers, vpon much weaker grounds, as difference of ſtiles, or the like.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In another place you tell vs<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pag. 68. n. 43.</note> that to receiue a Booke for Canonicall, it is inough to haue <hi>had atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation though not vniuerſall, yet at least ſufficient to make conſidering men receiue them for Canonicall, which were
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2349:23"/>ſometimes doubted of by ſome, yet whoſe number and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority was not ſo great, as to preuaile against the contrary ſuffrages.</hi> Obſerue vpon what inextricable paſſages, and leſſe degrees of probability this man doth put vs in our beliefe of holy Scripture. Firſt we muſt ſettle our Fayth on <hi>men;</hi> then on <hi>conſidering</hi> men, though the conſent be not vniuerſall; thirdly vpon the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more preualent number and authority of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages, as if the greater number alone, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, were a ſufficient ground for Chriſtian Fayth. You deny (pag. 68. n. 42.) that the Controuerſy about Scripture is to be tryed by moſt voyces, and yet what is your greater number, but moſt voyces? And as for greater <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> what can you meane thereby, except perhaps greater learning, or ſome ſuch quality, nothing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to that <hi>Authority,</hi> on which Chriſtian Fayth muſt relye?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Doctrine.</hi> That the Apostles were not infallible in their writings, but erred with the whole Church of their time.</head>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT can be no wonder that he ſhould ſpeake meanly of the neceſſity, and infallibility of holy Scripture, ſince he labours to faſten er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour vpon the Canonicall writers, and deliuerers thereof the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelues, and the <hi>whole Church</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2349:24"/>of their time.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</note> And this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning an Article of Fayth of higheſt conſequence and moſt frequently reuealed in holy Scripture, the deniall whereof had byn moſt derogatory from the glory of our Sauiour, and from the abundant fruit of his ſacred Paſsion: to wit, that the Ghoſpell was to be preached to all nations. You ſhall receiue it in his owne words:<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pag. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. n. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church may ignorantly disbelieue a Reuelation, which by errour ſhe thinkes to be no Reuelation. That the Goſpell was to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to all Nations, was a Truth reuealed before our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Aſcenſion in theſe words; Goe and teach all nations. Math.</hi> 29.19. <hi>Yet through preiudice, or inaduertence, or ſome other cauſe the Church disbelieued it, as it is apparent out of the</hi> 11. <hi>and</hi> 12. <hi>Chapter of the Acts, vntill the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Cornelius.</hi> And that the Apoſtles themſelues were inuolued in this ſuppoſed errour of the moſt primitiue Church, he deliuers without ceremony in another place:<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 144. <hi>n.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Apoſtles themſelues euen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſending of the holy Ghost were, and through inaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or preiudice continued for a time, in an errour repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to a reuealed Truth, it is, as I haue already noted, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerably euident from the ſtory of the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi> Is not this to ouerthrow all Chriſtianity? If the Bleſſed Apoſtles on whom Chriſtians are builded, as vpon their foundation (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.) were obnoxious to <hi>inaduertence,</hi> to <hi>preiudice,</hi> to <hi>other cauſes</hi> of errour; what certainty can we now haue? The Apoſtles might haue written what they belieued, and ſo we cannot be ſure but what they haue written may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome errour proceeding from <hi>inaduertence, preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> or ſome other cauſe. If they euen after the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the holy Ghoſt, and with them the whole
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2349:24"/>Church of that time, could either forget or tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſo freſh a Commaund, impoſed by our Sauiour Chriſt for his laſt farewell at his Aſcenſion; it will be obuious for aduerſaries of Chriſtian Religion to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, that perhaps they haue byn left to themſelues, to obliuion, inaduertence, and other humane defects in penning the Scripture. If they erred in their firſt thoughts, why not in their ſecond? With the aſsiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the holy Ghoſt they can erre in neither, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, in both.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Obiection which he brings is not hard to ſolue. <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelfe neuer doubted. That viſion was ſhewed to him, and he declared it to the conuerted Iewes for their ſatisfaction, as it happened in the Councell held by the Apoſtles, about the obſeruation of the law of <hi>Moyſes;</hi> which ſome Chriſtians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted from Iudaiſme did much vrge. But neither the Apoſtles, nor the other Chriſtians had any doubt in that matter: as likewiſe in our preſent caſe, not all the Church, but only ſome Zealous for the Iewes did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues to <hi>S. Peter.</hi> For before the conuerſion of <hi>Cornelius</hi> other Gentils were become Chriſtians, as<note n="(o)" place="margin">Com. in Act. cap. <hi>10.</hi> post verſ. <hi>48,</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> with others affirmes &amp; proues. For which reſpect the text expreſsely declares,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Act. c. 11. v. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> that they who were offended with <hi>S. Peter were of the circumciſion,</hi> that is Iewes made Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He goes on in this conceit, and addes a point no leſse daungerous then the former. <hi>The Apostles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> ſayth he,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pag. 144. n. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>was confirmed by miracles, therefore it was entirely true, and in no part either falſe, or vncertain. I ſay in no part which they deliuered constantly, as a certaine diuine truth, and which had the attestation of diuine mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2349:25"/>Thus you ſee he couertly calls in queſtion all the Apoſtles writings, and layes grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to except againſt them. For if once we giue way to ſuch diſtinctions, and ſay that the Apoſtles are to be credited only, in what they <hi>deliuered constantly as a certaine diuine Truth;</hi> we may reiect in a manner all Scripture, which ſcarce euer declares, whether or no the writers thereof did deliuer any thing, as a certaine diuine Truth; and much leſſe that they remained conſtant in what they deliuered by writing. Or if it ſhould expreſse theſe particulars, yet we could not be obliged to belieue it, if once we come to deny to the Apoſtles an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall infallibility. For what reaſon can this man giue, according to theſe grounds of his, why they might not haue erred in that particular declaration?</p>
               <p n="4">4. And beſides, will he not oblige vs to belieue with certainty any thing deliuered by the Apoſtles which had not <hi>the attestation of diuine miracles?</hi> It ſeeemes he will not, and thereby in effect takes away the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of very many myſteries of Chriſtian Fayth and verities contayned in holy Scripture. For that mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were wrought in confirmation of euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular paſſage of Scripture, we cannot affirme neither out of holy Scripture it ſelfe, nor any other credible argument: rather the contrary is certaine, there being innumerable verityes of the Bible which were neuer ſeuerally confirmed in that manner, and yet it were damnable ſinne to deny them. And moreouer where, or when did the Apoſtles particularly prooue by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, that their writings were the word of God? Thus you ſee into what plunges he brings all Chriſtians by his owne <hi>Inconſtancy;</hi> from which certainly ariſeth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2349:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>this itching deſire of his to put conceites into mens heades, as if the Apoſtles alſo might haue byn va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their writings and not conſtant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I cannot omit another diſtinction preiudiciall to the infallibility of the Apoſtles &amp; of their writings, which he deliuereth in theſe words:<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 144. <hi>n.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>For thoſe things which the Apoſtles profeſſed to deliuer, as the Dictates of human reaſon, and prudence, and not as diuine Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, why ſhould we take them as diuine Reuelations? I ſee no reaſon, nor how we can do ſo, and not contradict the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and God himſelfe. Therefore when S. Paul ſayes in the</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt. to the Corinth.</hi> 7.12. <hi>To the rest ſpeake I, not the Lord. And againe: Concerning virgins I haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment of the Lord, but I deliuer my iudgment. If we will pretend that the Lord did certainly ſpeake what S. Paul ſpake, and that his iudgment was Gods commandment, ſhall we not plainly contradict S. Paul, and that ſpirit by which he wrote which mooued him to write; as in other places diuine Reuclations, which he certainly knew to be ſuch, ſo in this place his owne Iudgment touching ſome things, which God had not particularly reuealed vnto him.</hi> This doctrine is ſubiect to the ſame iuſt exceptions, which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged againſt the former. For if once we deny vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall infallibility to the Apoſtles, we cannot belieue them with infallibility in any one thing, but ſtill we may be doubting whether they ſpeake out of their owne ſpirit, and not by diuine Reuelation, though they ſhould euen declare in what ſort they intend to ſpeake, becauſe we may feare they are deceiued in thoſe very declarations. And as you will perhaps ſay, they write Diuine Reuelations, except in things which they profeſſe to deliuer <hi>as the Dictates of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2349:26"/>human reaſon and prudence;</hi> another will ſay that they muſt or may be vnderſtood to deliuer <hi>the dictats of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reaſon and prudence,</hi> whenſoeuer they do not in expreſſe rearmes profeſſe to deliuer diuine Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is very ſeldome; the ordinary cuſtome of holy Scripture being to deliuer verityes without any ſuch qualifying of them. And if <hi>S. Paul</hi> when in the Epiſtle and Chapter by you cited <hi>v.</hi> 40. ſayes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>I thinke that I alſo haue the ſpirit of God,</hi> might be deceiued in that thought of his; we may alſo ſay he might be deceiued, euen when he affirmes that he writes by the ſpirit of God; and much more may we doubt, when he expreſſes no ſuch thing, as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neither he, nor any other Canonicall writers doe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the words which you cite: <hi>To the reſt ſpeake I, not the Lord, S. Paul</hi> treates of a very important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, of the wiues departing from her husband, or the husbands from his wife. Wherein if <hi>S. Paul</hi> were ſubiect to errour, he might chance to haue taught a point of great Iniuſtice, againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of our Sauiour declaring the very Law of nature, <hi>What God hath ioyned togeather let not man ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi>
                  <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.6.</note>. And as for the words you alleadge in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place: <hi>Concerning virgins I haue no commandment of our Lord, but I deliuer my Iudgment,</hi> the Apoſtle after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards within the compaſſe of the ſelfe ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſayes that a man ſinnes not if he marry; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if <hi>S. Paul</hi> may be deceiued, as ſpeaking out of his owne ſpirit, as you ſay he doth in ſome precedent words; you will not only want this text to prooue with certainty, that marriage is lawfull, but when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer marriage is allowed in any other place of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2349:26"/>Scripture (as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Marriage is honourable in all</hi>) you haue put into the mouthes of the old and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne heretiques, who impugned the lawfullnes of marriage, a ready anſwere that thoſe texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, were but the Dictats of human reaſon and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, wherein the writers of Canonicall Scripture might be deceiued.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The other words, <hi>Speake I, not the Lord,</hi> ſhew only that our Sauiour left power for the Apoſtles, and his Church to aduiſe, counſaile, ordaine, or commaund ſome things, as occaſion might require, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had not commaunded, or determined in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: which truth if you hold to be only a <hi>Dictate of human reaſon,</hi> you open a way for refractary ſpirits to oppoſe the ordinances of their Superiours and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, in things not expreſſely commaunded by our Lord.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The laſt Words <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>Concerniug virgins I haue no commandment of the Lord, but I deliuer my Iudgment,</hi> which we tranſlate, <hi>but I giue counſaile,</hi> prooue indeed our Catholicke Doctrine concerning workes of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation, or Counſayles, in regard that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in this place perſuades virginity as the better, but commaunds it not as neceſſary: Yet they do in no wiſe imply any doubtfulneſſe or fallibility in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; neuer any hitherto beſides your ſelfe, offering to anſwere our argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by ſaying, the Apoſtle wrote only the dictate of human reaſon, or prudence, and ſo might be deceiued. Which anſwere had been very obuious, if they had preſumed to be ſo bold, as you are, with the Apoſtles, and therefore it is a ſigne that no man beſides your ſelfe durſt deliuer this doctrine.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2349:27"/>
               <p n="9">9. Certainly if the Apoſtles did ſometimes write by the motion of the holy Ghoſt, and at other times out of their owne priuate Iudgment or ſpirit; though it were granted that themſelues could diſcerne the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of thoſe motions or ſpirits (which one may eaſily deny, if their vniuerſall infallibility be once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached) yet it is cleere that others, to whom they ſpake or wrote, could not diſcerne the diuerſity of thoſe ſpirits in the Apoſtles. For which cauſe learned Proteſtants acknowledge, that although ech mans priuate ſpirit were admitted for direction of himſelfe, yet it were not vſefull for teaching others. Thus you ſay (pag. 141.) A ſupernaturall aſſurance of the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Scripture may be an aſſurance to ones ſelfe, <hi>but no argument to another.</hi> And as you affirme<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>that bookes that are not Canonicall may ſay they are, and thoſe that are ſo, may ſay nothing of it:</hi> ſo we cannot be aſſured that the Apoſtles deliuer diuine Reuelations, though they ſhould ſay they doe; nor that they deliuer not ſuch Reuelations though they ſay nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if once we deny their vniuerſall infallibility.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Now I beſeech the good Reader to reflect vpon this mans endeauours to ouerthrow the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Chriſtianity, and to what at laſt he tends by theſe degrees. Firſt he ſayth, our beliefe that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the word of God exceedes not probability. 2. Amongſt thoſe Bookes which we belieue to be the word of God, we belieue ſome with leſſe probability then others. Thirdly we may be ſaued though we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belieue that Scripture is the Rule of Fayth, nor that it is the word of God. Fourthly, our aſſurance that Scripture or any other Booke is corrupted, is of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2349:27"/>the ſame kind and condition, both, <hi>only morall aſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</hi> Fifthly the writers of holy Scripture might erre in things which they deliuered not conſtantly, or not as diuine Reuelations, but dictates of human reaſon, or if they deliuered any doctrine not confirmed by miracles. Sixtly, vpon the ſame ground he might ſay that the Apoſtles were infallible only when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered things belonging to Fayth, Piety, or Religion, &amp; not when they wrote things meerely indifferent, or of no great moment in themſelues, as ſome <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> Dom. Lopez. de Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. ſac. Script.</note> eyther grant, or care not much to deny. And then further it will be left to euery mans iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, what is to be accounted a matter of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And ſoone after it will be ſaid, that to ſearch whether the doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, be contained in Scripture, or no, is not much neceſſary; ſince a man without knowledge of that ſpeculatiue doctrine, may belieue and loue God, as a chiefe <hi>Socinian</hi> teaches<note n="(w)" place="margin">Iren. Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leth. diſſerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione de Pace Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae.</note> and your ſelfe affirme<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 37.</note> 
                  <hi>that any Fayth if it worke by loue ſhall certainly auaile with God, and be accepted of him.</hi> And then will ſome ſay; Why may not a man loue <hi>God</hi> though he erre in the doctrine concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> deliuered in Scripture? &amp; ſo it will not be neceſſary to belieue that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were infallible in penning the Scripture, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in articlesd abſolutely neceſſary to loue God, and to haue a generall ſorrow for all our ſinnes. And ſince to loue God &amp; haue contrition for our ſinnes, a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beliefe will ſerue according to your<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 327.</note> Principles, what need we any infallible Scripture at all, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome motiues ſufficient to produce a probable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that there is a God, whether it be by Scripture
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2349:28"/>belieued to be only a probable writing, or by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſcourſe, or any other meanes; as you teach, that one is not bound to belieue the Scripture to be the word of God, but may be ſaued, if by other meanes, for example, preaching, he attaine the knowledge of the verityes contayned in Scripture<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 116.</note>. And thus you ſee to what hauock theſe things lead, not only touching Chriſtianity, but of all Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Doctrine.</hi> Iniurious to the miracles of our Sauiour, and of his Apoſtles.</head>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE Diſciple is not aboue his Mayſter: &amp; we may not wonder that a man ſhould be free with the Apoſtles, if he ſpare not Chriſt himſelfe. To the end that the entrance might be proportionable to the building which he was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, he plants in his Preface a Tenet, which cannot but be as ſtrange to all conſiderate Chriſtians, as it is dangerous to the weake. It ſeemes he was not able to deny, that true miracles haue been wrought by mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Catholicke Church: He comes therefore to this deſperate euaſion, and giues vs theſe wordes in print:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pref. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It ſeemes to me no ſtrange thing, that God in his Iuſtice ſhould permit ſome true miracles to be wrought to delude them who haue forged ſo many, as apparently the Profeſſours of the Roman doctrine haue to abuſe the world.</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2349:28"/>I ſhall wrong the Readers vnderſtanding, if for his ſake I ſhall ſtand to dilate vpon that, which is very cleer; that by this meanes the miracles of our Bleſſed Sauiour, and his Apoſtles cannot be knowne to be inducements to truth, but may haue been ſnares to entrap the behoulders in pernicious errours. To what end then doth <hi>S. Paul</hi> prooue his miſſion by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles?<note n="(b)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Signa Apostolatus meifacta ſunt ſupervos, in omni prudentia, in ſignis, &amp; prodigijs &amp; virtutibus.</hi> To what end did our Bleſſed Sauiour aſſigne miracles, to confirme the preaching of his Apoſtles? <hi>Signa autem eos, qui crediderint, hae ſequentur: In nomine meo daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia eijcient &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Mare. vlt. v. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note>. To what purpoſe did he ſend this meſſage to <hi>S. Iohn Baptist, Caecivident, claudi ambulant</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> II.</note>? To what end did he ſay<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi opera non feciſſem in eis, quae nemo alius fecit, peccatum non haberent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Many other texts might be alledged. Theſe will ſatisfy euery good Chriſtian that belieues the Scriptures. But I confeſſe, neither theſe or any other places of Scripture can prooue any thing with this man, who by affirming that true miracles may be wrought to delude men, doth depriue the Apoſtles of all authority which they could gayne by working miracles, and conſequently leaues men free from any obligation to belieue that their writings were infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible. And then to what purpoſe doth he tel vs in the ſame place, that the Bible hath byn <hi>confirmed with thoſe miracles, which were wrought by our Sauiour Christ and his Apoſtles,</hi> ſince thoſe very miracles might by the ſame ground, be deluſions rather then confirmations? If true miracles may now be wrought in puniſhment of Chriſtians for forging falſe miracles, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2349:29"/>what certainty can you giue a man that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; his Apoſtles did not the like,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</note> in puniſhment of the Iewes and Gentils for Idolatry, Irreligiouſneſſe and other grieuous ſinnes, which are neuer wanting in the world, and may be puniſhed in the manner you ſpeake of, if once this aſſertion be admitted, that <hi>True miracles may be wrought to delude men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But though by this impiety you depriue Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all authority, and cannot conſequently be perſuaded to any thing by Scripture: yet there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes one powerfull authority to conuince you euen in this your tenet. It is your ſelfe. For thus you ſpeake to vs vpon another occaſion:<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pag. 144. n. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Yf you be ſo infallible, as the Apostles were, shew it as the Apostles did. They went forth</hi> (ſayth S. Marke) <hi>and preached euery where, the Lord working with them, and confirming their words with ſignes following. It is impoſsible that God ſhould lye, &amp; that the eternall Truth should ſet his hand and ſeale to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of a falſhood, or of ſuch doctrine, as is partly true and partly falſe. The Apostles doctrine was thus confirmed, therefore it was intirely true, and in no part either falſe or vncertaine.</hi> Is it not cleere by theſe words that ſince the Doctrine of the Roman Church hath byn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by true miracles (as you affirmed in your Motiue, and for ought I can perceiue, deny it not in your anſwere) ſhe muſt be the true Church? For euen againſt your ſelfe, when you ſpeake not in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Roman Church, you confeſſe that the eternall Truth cannot confirme a falſhood with true miracles. Or if in oppoſition to our Church you will recall what you deliuer in your Booke, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to that which you ſay in your Preface in anſwere
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2349:29"/>to your <hi>Motiue;</hi> I muſt ſtill be enforced to affirme that you prepare a way to the ouerthrow of Chriſtianity, by euacuating the efficacy of miracles wrought by Chriſt our Lord, his Apoſtles, and all holy men, in confirmation of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And to the end the Reader may not thinke I am too rigorous in preſſing you vpon this one paſſage, vpon which you were thruſt by a hard neceſsity of anſwering your owne motiues; I challenge you vpon this other wherein you ſay:<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pag. <hi>69.</hi> n. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>For my part I profeſſe, that if the Doctrine of the Scripture were not as good, and as fit to come from the fountaine of goodneſſe, as the miracles by which it was confirmed were great, I should want one maine pillar of my Fayth, and for want of it, I feare ſhould be much staggered in it.</hi> Catholickes are moſt certaine that the doctrine of the Scripture is as good, as the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles by which it was confirmed were great. But this certainty we do not ground vpon our owne Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Iudgment, framed by conſidering the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in themſelues, as if we ſhould <hi>be staggered</hi> if we could not find them to be ſuch independently of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; but, becauſe they are confirmed by miracles, or otherwiſe teſtifyed to be good, by them, to whom we muſt ſubmit: whereas your way of beliefe leaues a man in a diſpoſition to be perpetually altering opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, accordingly as the ſame things may ſometimes appeare true, and other times falſe; which diuerſity of iudgments you muſt according to this your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine follow, euen againſt any point confirmed by miracles, if it chance to ſeeme not true to your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which is the part and proper diſpoſition of a <hi>Socinian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2349:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fifth Doctrine.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</note>
                  </hi> By reſoluing Fayth into Reaſon, he destroyes the nature of Fayth and beliefe of all Chriſtian verityes.</head>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe ſource whence all the aforeſaid and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable other pernicious ſequels do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Gentle Reader, is, that according to this mans doctrine, <hi>Chriſtian Fayth</hi> muſt be reſolued into the euidence of naturall <hi>reaſon,</hi> not as preparing or inducing vs to belieue, but as the maine ground, &amp; ſtrongeſt pillar of our Fayth, and in a word, as the concluſion depends on the premiſes. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he builds much vpon this axiome:<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pag. 36. n. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>We cannot poſsibly be more certaine of the concluſion, then of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the premiſes; as a riuer will not riſe higher then the fountaine from which it flowes.</hi> Hence in the ſame place he deduceth that the certainty of Chriſtian <hi>Fayth</hi> can be but <hi>morall,</hi> and not abſolutely <hi>infallible.</hi> With this principle is connexed another, vnleſſe you will call it the ſame more expreſſely declared and applyed. And it is this: If vpon reaſons ſeeming to my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding very good, I haue made choyce of a Guide or Rule for my direction in matters of Fayth; when afterward I diſcouer that this Guide or Rule leades me to belieue one or more points, which in the beſt iudgment that I can frame, I haue ſtronger reaſons to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2349:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>reiect, then I had to accept my former Rule; I may and ought to forſake that Rule as falſe &amp; erroneous: otherwiſe I ſhould be conuinced not to follow rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſome ſetled reſolution to hold faſt whatſoeuer I had once apprehended. What followes from this vaſt principle, but that if holy Scripture (for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) propound things ſeeming more euidently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to reaſon, or my opinion, more plainly contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting one another, then the inducements which firſt mooued me to belieue Scripture were ſtrong &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing; I muſt reiect the Scripture, as an erroneous Rule, and adhere to my owne Reaſon and diſcourſe as my laſt and ſafeſt guide. This certainly doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Eſpecially if we remember another principle that the motiues, for which we belieue holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are only probable, for ſo they muſt in all equity giue place to reaſons ſeeming demonſtratiue &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing, as there will not want many ſuch againſt the high miſteries of Chriſtian Fayth, if once we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that our aſſent to them muſt be reſolued into na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diſcourſe. How farre diſſonant this is from the receiued perſuaſion and tenet of all Chriſtians, that their Fayth is not reſolued into Reaſon but Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is eaſy to ſee by the effects. For why do <hi>Socinians</hi> and ſuch like deny the miſteryes of the Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Deity of our Bleſſed Sauiour, and diuers other verityes of Chriſtian Fayth, but becauſe they ſeeme manifeſtly repugnant to reaſon?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It cannot be doubted but that any one to whom the ſaluation of his owne ſoule is deare, will be wary in admitting doctrines deliuered in a Booke, if with Truth it may be affirmed, that the Author in point of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2349:31"/>beliefe is certainly no good Chriſtian, as one who denyes the Diuinity of Chriſt our Lord, and the moſt Bleſſed Trinity, which are miſteryes moſt proper to Chriſtian Fayth, and moſt hatefull to Iewes and Turkes. For what authority can he challenge with any iudicious Chriſtian, in matters concerning Fayth, who confeſſedly erres in the prime articles of Chriſtian Fayth? as we feare euen a ſound man, if we thinke he come from the peſt-houſe; and none will truſt the Diuell though transfigured into an Angell of light. For which cauſe ſpirituall men bid vs exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, not only what motions we find in our ſoule, but alſo from what roote they proceed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I wil not take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to ſay what you are, or what you are not, but in matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning articles of fayth we ought to ſpeak plainly. You tell vs<note n="(i)" place="margin">Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. n. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue <hi>the Doctrine of the Trinity, the Deity of our Sauiour, and all other ſupernaturall verityes reuealed in Scripture.</hi> The queſtion is not, whether you belieue ſome kind of Trinity, nor whether our Sauiour be God in ſome ſenſe by participation, as Dauid ſayes, <hi>I haue ſaid, you are Gods</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.6.) and in that ſenſe that they are contayned in Scripture: But the queſtion is whether you belieue thoſe miſteryes, as they are generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued by Chriſtians, and expreſſed euen in the 39. <hi>Articles</hi> of the Engliſh Church: or whether you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that in this ſenſe they are reuealed in Scripture. Be pleaſed then to declare your ſelfe, whether you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that <hi>in the Godhead there be three Perſons of one ſubstance, Power, and Eternity, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghost, as is taught in the firſt article.</hi> And then whether you belieue the <hi>ſecond Article,</hi> wherein is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2349:31"/>ſaid: <hi>The Sonne which is the word of the Father, the very and eternall God of one ſubstance with the Father, tooke mans nature in the wombe of the Bleſsed Virgin, of her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: So that two whole and perfect natures, that is to ſay, the Godhead and Manhood were ioyned togeather in one Perſon neuer to be deuided, whereof is one Chriſt very God, and very Man.</hi> Thirdly, whether you firmely belieue the contents of the fifth <hi>Article: The holy Ghost procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the Father and the ſonne, is of one ſubstance, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty, and Glory with the Father and the ſonne, very eternall God.</hi> If theſe demaunds ſeeme harſh, blame your ſelfe who were forewarned, euen before that which they call the <hi>Direction</hi> was publiſhed, when it was in your power to haue freed your ſelfe from this trouble, and ſecured others from the ſcandall which your Booke may giue. Neither are theſe queſtions from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but conſequent to principles deliuered in your Booke.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And let no man wonder, that I deſire plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For I haue ſeene a <hi>Socinian</hi> Catechiſme in print, which at firſt grants that Chriſt is God, but then to the queſtion, whether he haue the <hi>diuine Nature,</hi> it anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, No: becauſe (forſooth) that is a thing repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant both to Scripture and Reaſon. It is apparent that the <hi>Socinians</hi> agree with the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> that <hi>Fayth</hi> is reſolued into <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that the <hi>Manicheans</hi> maintained a moſt ſtrict brotherhood with the <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillianiſts,</hi> who taught that it is lawfull to diſſemble a mans Fayth euen by oath: For their ſaying was, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, periura, ſecretum prodere noli.</hi> And <hi>Arius,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Diuinity of our Sauiour Chriſt, made no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to forſweare himſelfe by a profeſsion of Fayth,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2349:32"/>contrary to his internall beliefe. And whether any one who is eſteemed a <hi>Socinian</hi> do not hold it lawfull to deny, or ſpeake ambiguouſly againſt what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues, that ſo in a very peruerſe ſenſe he may with the Apoſtle, <hi>become all to all,</hi> it is likely you know better then another can tell you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Howſoeuer, euery one doth now expect, that both for theſe and other manifeſt errours mentioned in that litle Booke of Direction, you openly declare your ſelfe: it being not ſufficient to ſay, as you do, in a generall confuſed manner,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer teaches, or holdes them, let him be Anathema.</hi> For this vniuerſality or collection of errours, in a confuſed ſort, leaues an euaſion to make good your ſpeach, if you reiect but any one of thoſe errours, through withall you imbrace the reſt. And therefore to acquit your credit, and to take away ſcandal, it were your part to renounce ech one in particular. For if in any occaſion, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this, ſilence ought to be interpreted a confeſsion of the ſaid errours. <hi>S. Hierome</hi> is of this mind, when he ſayes,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ep. <hi>75.</hi> adu. Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> 
                  <hi>Nolo in ſuſpicione Haereſeos quemquam eſse pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientem, ne apud eos, qui ignorant innocentiam eius, diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio conſcientia iudicetur, ſi taceat.</hi> It you be not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I do you a ſingular fauour, in giuing you this fayre and ſit occaſion, to wipe of that publicke ſtaine which report hath caſt on you, and wherof you haue not only giuen too great occaſion by your owne words in frequent Conferences, but now by your writings, which being publiſhed after the <hi>Direction,</hi> demonſtrates how deeply <hi>Socinian</hi> errours are rooted both in your iudgment &amp; affection, which could not be abated, either by priuate aduiſe, or publicke ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2349:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="6">6. But to returne from this neceſſary digreſsion; This your reſoluing Fayth into naturall Reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues occaſion for others at leaſt, if your ſelfe be guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, to deny the Diuinity of our Sauiour Chriſt, and conſequently to deny that he redeemed mankind by his Death; which if he be not true God, had beene (O blaſphemy!) not a price for our Redemption, but a puniſhment rather of his either vſurping the name of the true Sonne of God, or at leaſt for giuing men cauſe to belieue he did ſo. Theſe I grant are harſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and yet you cannot auoyd them, ſo long as you limit Chriſtian Fayth to probabilities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue ſolue theſe into naturall diſcourſe, as the <hi>concluſion</hi> into the <hi>premiſes.</hi> And giue me leaue to ſay, you do but diſſemble to circumuent an vnwary Reader, when you ſay,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> that you ſubmit <hi>all other reaſons to this one. God hath ſai ſo: Therefore it is true.</hi> For you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the maine point, which is, that you cannot know, that <hi>God hath ſaid ſo,</hi> except by motiues of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility, which can produce only a probable aſſent; and this muſt yield to the contrary, if it ſeeme eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by conuincing arguments, as <hi>Socinians</hi> conceiue their reaſons againſt the Bleſsed Trinity, and the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Sauiour Chriſt, to be. The like I ſay of other high miſteryes of Chriſtian Fayth; and ſtill muſt conclude, that vnder colour of vphoulding your cauſe you ouerthrow Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2349:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſixth Doctrine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</note> Deſtructiue of the Theologicall Vertues of Chriſtian Hope, and Charity.</head>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe grounds which he hath layd for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of <hi>Christian Fayth,</hi> doe by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ouerthrowe alſo Chriſtian <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and bring them downe to the ranke of ordinary <hi>Morall</hi> vertues. But not content with this, he hath other paſſages, in which he ſtrikes more neere the roote, and deliuers doctrines which tend imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly to the deſtruction of them. <hi>It is,</hi> ſayth he,<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 368.</note> 
                  <hi>against reaſon and experience, that by the commiſsion of any deadly ſinne, the Habit of Charity is quite extirpated.</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and experience are his Guides, you ſee, in all the moſt ſupernaturall buſineſſes of our ſoules. Reaſon and experience, as it ſeemes, do tell him, that euen when he is committing a mortal ſinne, that is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringing the commaundment of God in a matter of weight and moment, and in effect ſaying, I will not ſerue him; he is not withſtanding in Chriſtian <hi>Charity</hi> with him, and his <hi>humble ſeruant.</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Charity,</hi> as all Chriſtians are taught, is a ſupernaturall infuſed <hi>Habit,</hi> whereby we doe loue and preferre God before all things, and are habitually inclined to it. When we do not preferre him before all things, but turne our ſelues to Creatures by ſome ouerweeing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2349:33"/>to them, that act of commiſsion or omiſsion, if it be as I ſaid Mortall, is not only to be conſidered as an Act, but as an Act killing the ſoule, and bereauing it of the life thereof, that is of <hi>Charity,</hi> whereby only we liue in God: and conſequently the Infuſed Habit of <hi>Charity</hi> ceaſeth in vs: howſoeuer we may find by experience ſome inclination ſtill to loue God, either by ſome repetition of former acts of our owne, or rayſed by ſome conſideration repreſented to vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is the doctrine receiued amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt Chriſtians, which I do not now vndertake to diſpute, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare at large, but reſerue it for a larger worke; my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this being only to point out the heades from whence very ill conſequences muſt needes follow, that people may take heed of them, and not be too greedy of ſuch nouelties, leaſt togeather with them they ſucke their euerlaſting bane. For to goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to what paſſe would this one doctrine bring a Commonwealth or Kingdome if it were receaued? Certainly to all licentiouſneſſe and liberty. For if deadly ſinne may conſiſt with the Habit of Charity, much more with the Habit of <hi>Fayth</hi> and <hi>Hope.</hi> And it being certain amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtians, that God will damne no man in whoſe ſoule he beholds the precious gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of theſe three Theologicall vertues <hi>Fayth, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> it will be concluded, that deadly ſinne vnrepented cannot exclude a man from Heauen. An errour moſt pernicious, and to be baniſhed the thoughts of euery Chriſtian Man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the vertue of <hi>Hope,</hi> if I vnderſtand him right, he ſometimes deſtroyes it by <hi>Preſumption</hi> with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much largeneſſe, and ſometimes turnes it to <hi>Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2349:34"/>by denying ſinners a poſſibility to be ſaued, euen with the beſt repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that they can haue. In proofe of too much largeneſſe it will be ſufficient to allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge words, wherin he ſpeakes thus to Catholicks:<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>This pretenſe of yours, that Contrition will ſerue without actuall Confeſsion, but Attrition will not, is a nicety, or phanſy, or rather, to giue it the true name, a deuiſe of your owne to ſerue ends and purpoſes; God hauing no where decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe, but that whereſoeuer he will accept of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance which you are pleaſed to call Contrition, he will accept of that which you call Attrition. For though he like beſt the bright-flaming Holocauſt of Loue, yet he reiects not the ſmoaking flame of that repentance (if it be true and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall) which proceeds from Hope and Feare.</hi> Heere he is very large, and againſt all good Diuinity will nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue an Act proceeding from <hi>Hope</hi> or Feare, to be a ſufficient and proportionable diſpoſition to the nobleſt of the three Theologicall vertues <hi>Charity.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Proteſtant Deuines there want not ſome who are ſo farre from belieuing, that ſorrow ariſing from <hi>Feare</hi> of Hell, is ſufficient for remiſsion of ſinnes, that they hold it rather to be a ſinnefull Act.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But neither in this doe I intend for the preſent to enter into long diſputation, and therefore goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſhew that in other places of his Booke, he is as ſtrict. For he calls<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 292.</note> 
                  <hi>it a doctrine of Licentiouſneſſe, that though a man liue and dye without the practiſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian vertues, and with the Habits of many damnable ſinnes vnmortified, yet, if he in the last moment of his life, haue any ſorrow for his ſinnes, and ioyne confeſsion with it, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he ſhall be ſaued.</hi> I ſee not how this agrees with his former doctrine, that <hi>Attrition,</hi> and not only <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2349:34"/>is ſufficient for remiſſion of ſinnes. It is his part to reconcile and vindicate from contradiction his owne aſſertions. For me it is ſufficient that euery body may be apt inough to inferre from hence, that by this meanes a poore ſinner muſt deſpayre, though he haue euen <hi>Contrition</hi> of his ſinnes. For in thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, he hath no tyme <hi>for the practiſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian vertues,</hi> nor for the mortifying <hi>the habits of many damnable ſinnes,</hi> if he meane the acquired phyſicall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of vice, produced by former vicious acts, as he muſt vnderſtand if he meane to ſay any thing. For if by Habits of vice he vnderſtand Habituall ſinnes, or ſinnes remayning not ſufficiently retracted by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, it is to beg the queſtion, as if he ſhould ſay ſuch repentance is inſufficient for pardon of our ſinnes, becauſe it takes not away our ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But he does more cleerly declare himſelfe, and caſt men vpon deſperation, by what he ſayes of vs in another place:<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag:</hi> 392.</note> That although we prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>to be rigid defenders, and ſtout Champions for the neceſsity</hi> of Good workes, yet indeed we doe it, <hi>to make our owne fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions neceſsary, but obedience to God vnneceſsary: which will appeare</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>to any man who conſiders what strict neceſsity the Scripture impoſes vpon all men of effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall mortification of the Habits of all vices, and effectuall conuerſion to newnes of life, and vniuerſall obedience; and withall remembers, that an Act of Attrition, which you ſay with Priestly abſolution is ſufficient to ſaluation, is not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, which being a worke of difficulty and time, cannot be performed in an instant,</hi> and therefore neither <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor <hi>Contrition,</hi> which ſignifieth the moſt perfect kind of repentance will ſerue at ſuch an exigent. It is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2349:35"/>ſtrange, <hi>Attrition</hi> alone ſhould ſuffice for pardon of our ſinnes, and that it ſhould be inſufficient when it is ioyned with abſolution, which I hope you will not ſay, is ill, though you hold it not neceſſary. Or if you meane, that Attrition is ſufficient only when there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines further time for mortification of vicious ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, this anſwere ſeemes repugnant to your owne words, where ſpeaking of ſome kind of men, you ſay,<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> That notwithſtanding their errours, <hi>they may dye with Contrition, or if not with Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition, yet with Attrition,</hi> which, you ſay, God will accept. Which ſuppoſition of yours ſeemes either to ſpeake of dying men, or at leaſt to comprehend them. And (<hi>pag.</hi> 133.) you teach that for thoſe men that haue meanes to find the Truth and will not vſe them, though their caſe be daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, yet if they dye <hi>with a generall repentance for all their ſinnes knowne and vnknowne, their Saluation is not deſperate.</hi> Where you ſeeme alſo to ſpeake of men at the houre of their Death, when yet they haue not time to mortify the habits of vice. And indeed it is repugnant to Reaſon, that by Attrition a mans ſinnes ſhould be forgiuen, and yet this forgiueneſſe depend on the future performance of mortification, which you ſay requires time Howſoeuer, for my purpoſe it is ſufficient, that by denying poſsibility of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a repentant ſinner, at the laſt inſtant of his life, you vncharitably caſt men on deſperation, and deſtroy the <hi>Hope,</hi> yea and <hi>Fayth</hi> of Chriſtians, which aſſures vs, that forgiueneſſe is neuer denied to any that repents.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But there remaines yet a more daungerours er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that one may be ſaued with a generall repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2349:35"/>for his ſinnes, euen while he actually continues in them. This, vnleſſe I miſtake, is implyed in the words which I cited euen now<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 133.</note> that for thoſe who <hi>haue meanes to find the truth and will not vſe them, if they dye with a generall repentance for all their ſinnes knowne and vnknown, their ſaluation is not deſperate.</hi> Where you ſuppoſe, that a man remaines in a culpable errour, &amp; yet that a generall repentance may obtaine pardon without actuall dereliction of it. For if he forſake his errour, he is out of your caſe, which ſpeakes <hi>of men that haue meanes to find the Truth, and will not vſe them.</hi> A very eaſy pillow if it could be ſowed vnder any vnderſtanding eare. For if ſuch a generall repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce would ſuffice at the houre of death, it would alſo be ſufficient at other times, and conſequently one might haue pardon of his ſinnes whilſt he is actually committing them. Or if this be not the meaning of that paſſage, it wil notwithſtanding be true, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorrow is ſufficient to obtaine pardon for ſinnes, when there remaines no time to mortify the habits of vice, which is againſt your Tenet; or elſe that a ſinner cannot obtaine pardon at the hower of his Death, euen with repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2349:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeauenth Doctrine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</note> Takes away the grounds of rationall diſcourſe.</head>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT may ſeeme ſtrange, that a man ſhould reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue <hi>Chriſtian Fayth</hi> into <hi>naturall Reaſon,</hi> and yet fall vpon a way which deſtroyes all diſcourſe of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But to theſe exigents human Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is brought, when it forſakes the ground of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity.</hi> He teacheth, and endeauoureth to prooue<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pag. 215. &amp; <hi>217.</hi> n. 47.</note> by no fewer then ſeauen reaſons, that it is poſsible to aſſent to contradictions at the ſelfe ſame time. If a man wil ſpeake in this to the purpoſe, he muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of formall and direct contradictions; for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Chriſt is the Sauiour of the world: Chriſt is not the Sauiour of the world. Whereof to haue put thee in mind, good Reader, ſhall ſuffice at this preſent, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the breuity which in this diſcourſe I haue propoſed to my ſelfe, not doubting but thou wilt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this reflection and thyne owne examination find that all his ſeauen arguments, are very weake, and ſo farre from proouing his Aſſertion, that all of them, not one excepted, ſhew directly the contrary of that which he intended, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that as it ſeemes of purpoſe he tooke this ſubiect in taske to ſhew ſome ſtraine of wit, and to purchaſe ſome opinion of knowledge in Metaphyſicke.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How it hath thriued in his hand, tyme may ſhew
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2349:36"/>in ſome other treatiſe. Where alſo perhaps ſome other ſubtiltyes or quircks will be ſifted: to wit, firſt, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fayth</hi> be properly <hi>Knowledge</hi> or <hi>Apprehenſion</hi>
                  <note n="(v)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 325. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note>, for he mightily miſtakes in Philoſophy. Secondly, Whether <hi>obſcure</hi> and <hi>euident</hi> be <hi>affections not of our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but of the obiect of it</hi>
                  <note n="(w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 328.</note>; which were a ſtrange kind of Philoſophy, as if we ſhould ſay, <hi>God in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> is <hi>obſcure</hi> and <hi>euident,</hi> becauſe ſome vnderſtand him with an <hi>obſcure,</hi> and others with a <hi>cleere</hi> or <hi>euident</hi> aſſent. Thirdly, his diſcourſe (<hi>pag.</hi> 69. <hi>n.</hi> 48.) about the eye, obiect, and act of Seeing, with the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he would make betweene them, and the obiect and act of Fayth, which muſt fall vpon an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy condemned in the Pelagians, beſides ſome miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in Philoſophy. Fourthly, another ſubtilty about the eſſence of Habits, and formall motiue, to any Act &amp;c. whereof he ſpeakes <hi>pag.</hi> 138. <hi>n.</hi> 24. and does after his manner miſtake. Then alſo it ſhalbe ſhewed with how little reaſon he deſpiſes<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pag. 195. n. 11.</note> the diſtinction of being obliged not to disbelieue, and of not being obliged explicitly to belieue; and with as litle declai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes bitterly (<hi>pag.</hi> 391. <hi>n.</hi> 8.) againſt the doctrine that ſome things are neceſſary becauſe they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, and others commaunded becauſe they are neceſſary. And finally, the Reader muſt not be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at that time of the recreation he will receiue by a ſpeciall ſubtilty indeed, about a ſaying in Charity maintayned, <hi>That the Creed was an abridgment</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">Pag. 227. n. 65.</note>. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of the like nature will be then brought to the touchſtone, and layd as flat, as now perhaps to ſome partiall men they may haue ſeemed lofty and learned. My purpoſe here is only to giue the Reader
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2349:37"/>warning,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</note> that there be in the current of his diſcourſe ſuch ſhelues, as by croſſing the general receiued prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples among Chriſtians, deſtroy <hi>Fayth,</hi> and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally by the ouerthrow of <hi>Fayth,</hi> come at length to ouerwhelme Reaſon it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The eight Doctrine.</hi> Opens a way to deny the B. Trinity, and other high miſteryes of Chriſtian Fayth.</head>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Cannot omit notwithſtanding here to ſhew, that one of the Reaſons which he brings to prooue, that one may at the ſelfe ſame tyme, yield aſſent to contradictories, muſt be ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt of his Doctrins, which do cleerly tend to the ouer throw of Chriſtianity. It is the third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherin he argues thus:<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 215.</note> 
                  <hi>They which do capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate their vnderſtandings to the beliefe of thoſe things, which to their vnderſtandings ſeeme irreconciliable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, may as well belieue reall contradictions (for the difficulty of belieuing ariſes not from their being repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but from their ſeeming to be ſo.) But you</hi> (he ſpeakes to vs Catholicks) <hi>do captiuate your vnderstandings to the beliefe of thoſe things, which ſeeme to your vnderstandings irreconciliable contradictions. Therefore it is as poſsible, &amp; eaſy for you to belieue thoſe that indeed are ſo.</hi> Change but a word, and inſteed of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> put <hi>Christians,</hi> and the Concluſion will be: Therefore <hi>it is as poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2349:37"/>and eaſy</hi> for Chriſtians to belieue contradictions <hi>that indeed are ſo,</hi> as to belieue thoſe which to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding <hi>ſeeme ſo.</hi> And ſeeing it is the common conceit of men, that one cannot at the ſame time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue contradictions; and he himſelfe acknowledges in the ſame place,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 217. <hi>n.</hi> 47.</note> that men ſhould not do ſo, and that to do ſo, is both <hi>vnreaſonable</hi> and very <hi>difficult;</hi> what will follow but that to belieue the higheſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes of Chriſtian Fayth, is, if not <hi>impoſsible,</hi> at leaſt <hi>very difficult,</hi> and <hi>vnreaſonable,</hi> and a thing that men ſhould not doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now that Chriſtians belieue myſteries which to human reaſon ſeeme to imply contradiction, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will not deny. For though all the myſteryes of Chriſtian Fayth be in themſelues moſt ſacred &amp; true, yet to the weake eye of human reaſon ſome of them ſeeme to be againſt the Goodneſſe of God: as that, <hi>Many are called,</hi> and <hi>few elected,</hi> it being in his power to haue <hi>elected,</hi> and preuented with congruous &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious Grace, as well thoſe many, as theſe few. And our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding is apt to be the more ſtaggard with the depth of this myſtery, by conſidering that Chriſt our Lord dyed for the ſaluation of all; and that euery thought, word, or worke of his was ſuperabundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient for the Redemption of infinite millions of worlds. Other points of Chriſtian Fayth appeare contrary to Gods infinite Mercy, and Iuſtice. Such is our beliefe, that for euery deadly ſinne committed in a moment, and perhaps in a matter ſeeming but a trifle, as the eating of an apple, he ſhould inflict an eternity of torments, if it be not repented. Or, that Infants can be iuſtly depriued of Beatitude in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2349:38"/>of Originall ſinne, to which they neuer concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any Act properly theirs. And it might haue been to good purpoſe, if this man had declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe directly in theſe two points, ſeeing he was not without good ground <hi>directed</hi> to doe ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But I goe on with the difficulty of Chriſtian verities. For as the former may ſeeme harſh and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſo others may ſeeme, as it were, ſilly, &amp; <hi>vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> if Fayth be reſolued, as this man will haue it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to human <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Others beare a ſhew of repugnance to the moſt receiued Principles of Philoſophy, and Metaphyſicke, as the Myſtery of the moſt Bleſſed Trinity. Others in appearance derogate from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme reſpect we owe to God, as the myſtery of the Incarnation and Death of the ſonne of God. Where I cannot but obſerue, that this man ſpeakes ſo irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſometimes, that it may giue iuſt occaſion for men to enquire what he belieues concerning the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity of our Sauiour Christ, as when he ſayth;<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that the Doctrine of Tranſubstantiation may bring a great many others, as well, as himſelfe to Auerroes his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Quandoquidem Chriſtiani adorant quod comedunt, ſit anima mea cum Philoſophis: ſeeing Christians adore what they eate, my ſoule be with the Philoſophers.</hi> Is this matter of eating our Sauiour ſuch a pill to your vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that rather then diſgeſt it you will turne Turke or Infidell? If you belieued indeed that our Sauiour Chriſt is truly God, you would not be ſcandalized that Chriſtians adore Him, who would and could be eaten, no more then Him who ſtood in need of <hi>eating,</hi> and whom the Iewes were able to wound and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and might <hi>haue eaten</hi> (euen in a Capharnaiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2349:38"/>ſauage manner, farre different from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we receiue him in the B. Sacrament) if it had beene his will to permit it. Perhaps for theſe reaſons, hauing ſubiected Fayth to Reaſon, you wiſh with <hi>Auerroes,</hi> a profeſſed enemy of Chriſtians, <hi>My ſoule be with the Philoſophers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. He giues another ſuſpicion of it in the paſſage following. For hauing alleadged diuers ſeeming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions in our Doctrine concerning the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Altar, he concludes,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 216. 217.</note> that if I (that is the Author of Charity Maintayned) <hi>cannot compoſe the repugnance, and that after an intelligible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then I must giue him leaue to belieue, that either we do not belieue Tranſubſtantiation, or els that it is no contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that men should ſubiugate their vnderstandings to the beliefe of contradictions;</hi> which yet, as I ſaid before, he iudgeth either <hi>impoſsible,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>vnreaſonable</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ibid.</note>. And who I pray, can vndertake againſt a cauilling wit, to anſwere all arguments obiected againſt the Bleſſed Trinity, Incarnation, and other ſublime ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes of Chriſtian Fayth, and <hi>compoſe</hi> all ſeeming <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnances after an intelligible manner?</hi> Deuines are not ignorant, what inexplicable difficulties offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, euen concerning the Deity it ſelfe, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Immutability, Freedom of will, voluntary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, knowledge of creatures, and the like. Muſt we then deny them, becauſe we are not able <hi>to compoſe all repugnances</hi> after <hi>an intelligible manner?</hi> It may ſeeme that you are of opinion that we muſt; to which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion if you adde another Doctrine of yours, That there is no Chriſtian Church aſſiſted with Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity fit to teach any man, euen ſuch articles as are fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2349:39"/>or neceſſary to ſaluation, but that euery one may, and muſt follow the Dictates of his owne reaſon, be he otherwiſe neuer ſo vnlearned: what wil follow, but a miſerable freedome, or rather neceſsity for men to reiect the higheſt, and moſt diuine miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſtian Fayth, vnleſſe you can either <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> all <hi>repugnances after a manner,</hi> euen <hi>intelligible</hi> to euery ignorant and ſimple perſon (which I hope you will confeſſe to be impoſſible) or els ſay, it is <hi>reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> for men to belieue contradictions at the ſame time, which by your confeſſion were very <hi>vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And here I appeale to your owne Conſcience, whether in true Philoſophy, the obiections which may be made againſt the myſtery of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the Incarnation of the ſonne of God, be not incomparably more difficult, then any which can be brought againſt Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiation. Some one whom you know could ſay in ſome company, where there was occaſion of arguing, <hi>Either deny the Trinity, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Tranſubstantiation;</hi> and it was anſwered, <hi>We will rather admit this, then deny that.</hi> And with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For if we reſpect human diſcourſe, there are more difficult obiections againſt that miſtery, then againſt this. And if we regard Reuelation, Scripture is more cleare for the reall preſence, and Tranſubſtantiation, then for the myſtery of the Bleſſed Trinity. But no wonder if they who reduce all certainty of Chriſtian Fayth to the weight of naturall reaſon, are well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vnder the name of Tranſubſtantiation, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, and all the prime verityes proper to Chriſtian Fayth. For
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2349:39"/>which cauſe I haue ſome reaſon, as I touched before,<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 6.</note> not to be ſatisfyed, that this man for all his brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of belieuing Scripture, doth make that account of it which Chriſtians doe, and ought to doe, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes the Reader with ſpecious words: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when ſpeaking of the holy Scripture he ſayes:<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 376.</note> 
                  <hi>Propoſe me any thing out of this Booke and require whether I belieue it or not, and ſeeme it neuer ſo incomprehenſible to human reaſon, I will ſubſcribe it with hand and hart, as knowing no demonstration can be stronger then this: God hath ſaid ſo: Therefore it is true.</hi> Theſe are glorious words, but contrary to his owne principles. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing Fayth into Reaſon, he cannot belieue that which to his reaſon ſeemes contradictory, but muſt thinke that the Motiues for which he receiues Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being but probable, and ſubiect to falſhood, muſt of neceſſity yield to arguments more then probable, and demonſtratiue to human reaſon. And how then can he ſubſcribe to Myſteryes <hi>incomprehenſible to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reaſon,</hi> and capable of obiections which cannot alwayes be anſwered, <hi>after a manner intelligible,</hi> as he requires? And conſequently he <hi>must,</hi> to vſe his owne words, <hi>giue me leaue to belieue, that either he doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue</hi> thoſe miſteryes, <hi>or els,</hi> that he <hi>ſubiugates his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding to the beliefe of ſeeming contradictions;</hi> which he acknowledges to be <hi>vnreaſonable,</hi> and a thing which <hi>men ſhould not doe,</hi> according to his owne words<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 217.</note>. And the Reader had need to take heed that he be not taken alſo with that proteſtation of his:<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 376.</note> 
                  <hi>I know no demonſtration can be ſtronger then this; God hath ſaid ſo: Therefore it is true:</hi> ſince he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that he knowes not that God hath ſaid ſo, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2349:40"/>then by probable inducements, and only by a probable aſſent. So that in fine this muſt be his <hi>strong demonſtration:</hi> Whatſoeuer God ſpeakes or reueales, is moſt certainly true: But I am not certaine, that God ſpeakes in the Scripture: Therefore I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that whatſoeuer is in Scripture is true. Behold his <hi>demonstration,</hi> that is, a very falſe Syllogiſme, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne diſcourſe in another place where he not only graunts, but endeauours to prooue that the <hi>minor</hi> of this Demonſtration exceedes not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, and conſequently cannot inferre a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion more them probable. Somewhat like to this is an other cunning ſpeach of his:<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 225. <hi>n.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>That he hartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues the Articles of our Fayth be in themſelues Truths, as certaine and infallible, as the very common principles of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, or Metaphyſicke.</hi> Which being vnderſtood of the <hi>Obiects,</hi> or <hi>Truths</hi> of Chriſtian Fayth <hi>in themſelues,</hi> is no priuiledge at all. For euery Truth is in it ſelfe as certaine as the Principles of Geometry, it being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſsible that a Truth can be falſhood. But the point is, that he does not certainely know or belieue theſe Truths, as he does the Principles of Metaphyſicke, but onely with a probable aſſent, and ſo to him the Truths cannot be certaine. The like art alſo he vſes <hi>pag.</hi> 357. ſaying in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: <hi>I doe belieue the Goſpell of Christ, as verily as that it is now day, that I ſee the light, that I am now writing;</hi> for all this floriſh ſignifies only, that he is certaine he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieues the Goſpel of Chriſt with probable aſſent. As for the argument, it deſerues no anſwere. For who knowes not that contradictories inuolue two propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions? but he who captiuates his vnderſtanding, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2349:40"/>to one part only,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</note> and therefore is ſure inough not to belieue contradictories at the ſame time, as he pretends. All which conſidered, the Reader will eaſily ſee, that his Doctrines vndermine the chiefeſt myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſtian Fayth, and ouerthrow Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ninth Doctrine.</hi> Layes grounds to be conſtant in no Religion.</head>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p n="1">I. I Said in the beginning, that as we could not know the way, vnleſſe we firſt be told whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we goe; ſo it could litle auayle vs to be put in a way, if by following it we might be miſled. But ſuppoſe the end of our iourney be knowne, and the right way found, what better ſhall we be, if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we be continually harkning to ſome ſuggeſtions, which neuer let vs reſt, till we haue abandoned that path, by following other croſſe-wayes, as we chance to fall vpon them. This is the caſe of the man with whome we haue to deale. I will not build vpon his deeds, I meane his changes firſt from Proteſtant, to Catholique, then from Catholique to Proteſtant, &amp; then about againe to Catholique, till at laſt he be come to that paſſe, that it is hard to ſay, What he is, neyther <hi>Preciſian,</hi> nor Subſcriber to the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> nor confeſſed <hi>Socinian,</hi> nor right Chriſtian according to the grounds which he hath layd. If you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue himſelfe, for matters of Religion, he is conſtant in nothing, but in <hi>following that way to heauen which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2349:41"/>for the preſent ſeemes to him the moſt probable.</hi> He fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that which <hi>at the preſent ſeemes most probable:</hi> A poore comfort in matters of <hi>Fayth,</hi> wherin errour is of ſo great conſequence. And yet this cold comfort is vpon the point of being loſt; for the probability is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to <hi>the preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Would any man thinke that in matters of this nature, and after ſo much profeſsion that he is now ſatisfied, he ſhould<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> profeſſe himſelfe, <hi>still</hi> to haue a <hi>Trauellers indifferency, most willing to be led by reaſon to any way, or from it?</hi> And accordingly to tell vs,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That had there been repreſented to his vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch Reaſons for our Doctrine, as would haue made our Religion more credible then the contrary, certainly he should haue deſpiſed the ſhame of one more alteration, &amp; with both armes, and all his hart most readily haue imbraced it. Such was the preparation which he brought to the reading of that Booke,</hi> comming with <hi>ſuch a mind to the reading of it, as S. Austin before he was a ſetled Catholique, brought to his conference with Fauſtus the Manichee.</hi> Did <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was a ſetled Catholicke come with the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to conference with any Heretique or mis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuer? To what purpoſe then doth this man bring <hi>S. Austin</hi> here, but to ſhew the difference betwixt the <hi>Fayth</hi> of one that is a <hi>Catholicke,</hi> and of one that is not; the difference I ſay in point of <hi>adheſion</hi> to his <hi>Fayth,</hi> the Catholicke belieuing ſo aſſuredly that he may ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>If we, or an Angell from heauen euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelize</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>to you beſides that which we haue euangelized to you, be he Anathema.</hi> Others not being able euer to be certaine of what they belieue becauſe they build vpon grounds which by their owne confeſsion are not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2349:41"/>certaine and infallible.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In which reſpect alſo it may be iuſtly wondred with what ſenſe this man taking vpon him to be a guide to others, and to leade them a <hi>ſofe way</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, profeſſeth himſelfe not to be ſetled in his way, and ſtil to haue not only a<note n="(m)" place="margin">Prof. n. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Trauellers,</hi> but an Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Trauellers Indifferency,</hi> willing to be <hi>led</hi> to any way, or from it, becauſe he knowes not whether he be right or wrong; otherwiſe if he know himſelfe to be right, certainly it were not his part to be ſo willing to be led <hi>to any way, or from it:</hi> which giues me hope, that no man of iudgment, and timorous conſcience, will aduenture the eternall ſaluation of his ſoule, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the writings or Doctrine of one, who is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled, &amp; whom he either knowes not where to find, or how long to keep in any one opinion or profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; to whom the words of <hi>S. Bernard</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 193.</note> concerning <hi>Petrus Abailardus</hi> (who taught that <hi>Fayth</hi> was but <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>) may be applyed: <hi>Homo ſibi diſsimilis eſt, totus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguus. He is a man who diſagrees euen from himſelfe, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely compoſed of doubtings.</hi> I leaue out his middle words, <hi>intus Herodes, foris Ioannes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. One thing certainly people would be very glad to know, that whereas he maintaines, that his <hi>Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were the most ſatisfactory actions to himſelfe</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 303.</note> 
                  <hi>that euer he did, and the greatest victories that euer he obtained ouer himſelfe:</hi> Men, I ſay, would be glad to know vpon what new and great Motiues, theſe moſt <hi>ſatisfactory actions,</hi> &amp; <hi>greatest victoryes</hi> were ouer throwne againe, and frequent changes grounded. For his firſt being Catholicke, we haue Motiues in writing vnder his owne hand, and now in print. But what new reaſons
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2349:42"/>mooued him to forſake vs, this would people willin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly know. If he had no better reaſons, then be the anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to his owne Motiues, I ſcarcely belieue, that any iudicious Proteſtant will allow the alteration to haue been good, diuers of them being againſt Proteſtants themſelues, and ſome repugnant to all Chriſtianity, as may be well ſeene by the effects, which they haue wrought in him, to wit, ſo much vnſetledneſſe in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe and Religion, that he knowes not to this day, what he would be at. But we may well ſuppoſe that as he willingly leaues <hi>all men to their liberty, prouided that they improue it not to a Tyranny ouer others;</hi> ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the like liberty to himſelfe, and is in fine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to belieue <hi>whatſoeuer for the preſent doth ſeeme most probable to him:</hi> and ſo liuing in perpetuall Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, be an example to others to be conſtant in no profeſſion, which is as good as to be of no Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The tenth Doctrine.</hi> Prouides for the impunity &amp; preſeruation of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer damnable errour againſt Chriſtian Fayth.</head>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HE is no leſſe prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to conſerue then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious to beget Vnchriſtian errours &amp; Atheiſmes. Suppoſe an Orthodoxe Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall firſt into damnable Hereſies, then to Turciſme or Iudaiſme, afterward to Paganiſme, and finally to Atheiſme. Let him freely ſpeake his mind to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2349:42"/>and vnlearned, to high and low, to the Laity and Clergy, to all ſorts of perſons: Let him haue ſwarmes of followers, let Circumciſion be reduced, the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day obſerued for Sunday with Iewes, or Friday with the Turkes, and in confirmation of theſe ſacrileges, let Bookes be written. What remedy? Muſt theſe things be tolerated in a Chriſtian Common wealth, or Kingdome? with reſentment of a Chriſtian Prince? in deſpite of Chriſtian Prelates? vnder the eyes of Chriſtian Deuines? in the midſt of Chriſtian people? They muſt be ſuffered, if we belieue this mans do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 297.</note> that no man ought to be puniſhed for his opinions in Religion. <hi>We are willing</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>to leaue all men to their liberty, prouided they will not improue it to a Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ouer others</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 179. <hi>n.</hi> 81.</note>, a good meanes to preſerue euery one in his liberty without feare of puniſhment. <hi>And the contrary perſuaſion and practiſe,</hi> what is it? <hi>It well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them who haue their portions in this life, who ſerue no higher ſtate then that of England, or Spayne, or France, who thinke of no other happineſſe but the preſeruation of their owne fortunes, and tranquillity in this world, who thinke of no other meanes to preſerue States, but human power &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiauillian Policy.</hi> How daungerous to Church, &amp; euen to State this pernicious errour is, and what encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement it giues for vnquiet perſons to oppoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and how deepely it taxes England &amp; other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches of <hi>Machiauillian Policy,</hi> and <hi>to be men who haue their portions in this life, who ſerue no higher State then that of England, or Spayne, or France, who thinke of no other Happines, but the preſeruation of their owne fortunes in this world,</hi> for hauing puniſhed Heretiques euen with death, I leaue to be conſidered by higher Powers.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:2349:43"/>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.</note> I grant he would ſeeme to mitigate his doctrine, and confine it within certaine limits, but ſuch, that his exception is worſe then his generall Rule, vnleſſe I miſtake his meaning, &amp; therefore preſent his words as they lye to the Readers iudgment. <hi>There is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>no daunger to any State from any mans opinion, vnleſſe it be ſuch an opinion, by which diſobedience to Authority, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety is taught, or licenced; which ſort I confeſſe may iustly be puniſhed, as well as other faults: or vnleſſe this ſanguinary doctrine be ioyned with it, That its lawful for him by human violence to enforce others to it.</hi> Thus he. As for his firſt limitation, it either deſtroyes all that he ſaid before, or els it is but a verball gloſſe for his owne ſecurity. For if he grant that euery Hereſy is <hi>impiety,</hi> and brings with it <hi>diſobedience</hi> to Authority (as certainly it does, if it be profeſſed againſt the lawes of the Kingdome, or Decrees and Commaunds of the Church, State, &amp; Prelats where the contrary is maintained:) If, I ſay, his meaning be this, then his former generall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine vaniſheth into nothing; &amp; it will ſtill remaine true, that men may be puniſhed for their opinions &amp; hereſyes. But if his meaning be, that no opinion is to be puniſhed, except ſuch as implyes diſobedience to Authority, or licenſeth Impiety in things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long meerely to Temporall affayres, and concerne only the ciuill comportment of one man to another, as theft, murther, and the like; then he ſtill leaues a freedome for men to belieue, and profeſſe what they pleaſe for matters of Religion. And ſo, if they iudge a thing to be vnlawfull, which their Superiours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to be indifferent, yet they may hold their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and diſobey their Prelates, and may be able to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2349:43"/>tel them from this mans doctrine, that to enforce any man in points of this kind, is vnlawfull <hi>Machiauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Policy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. His ſecond limitation ſeemes to goe further, telling vs, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s opinion may be puniſhed, if this <hi>ſanguinary doctrine be ioyned with it, That it is lawfull for him by human violence to enforce others to it.</hi> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, for ought I can perceiue, it cleerly followes, that if any Church preſcribe ſome forme of Beliefe, and puniſh others for belieuing and profeſſing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Prelats or others of that Church, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to enforce by puniſhment ſuch contrary belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, may themſelues be iuſtly puniſhed. As if for example, an <hi>Arian</hi> be puniſhed with Death in any Kingdome, the Prelats, or other Perſons of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in that State, may according to his doctrine be lawfully puniſhed, as holding it lawfull to enforce men againſt their conſcience, which he calles a <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Doctrine.</hi> How daungerous a poſition this might prooue, if <hi>Arians,</hi> or <hi>Socinians,</hi> or any other ſect, or vnquiet ſpirit could preuaile in any Kingdome or Commonwealth where Hereticks are puniſhed, it is not fit for me to exaggerate; being ſufficient for my intention, to haue made it cleere, that the enemy of mankind could neuer haue inuented a more effectual meanes then this freedome of opinion, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement by impunity, for the enlarging of his infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Kingdome by Hereſy, Paganiſme, Atheiſme, and in a word, by deſtroying whatſoeuer belongs to Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for puniſhing Heretiks with Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in words he grants it may be done; but I haue
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2349:44"/>reaſon to ſuſpect what his meaning is indeed, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſpeake thus only for ſome reſpects. For I know that a great <hi>Socinian</hi> hath printed the contrary.<note place="margin">Iren. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lal. diſp. de Pace Eccleſ.</note> And if no man can be puniſhed with temporall puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for imbracing that which his Conſcience perſuades him to be Truth, how can he be lawfully puniſhed by Excommunication, for doing that which to his vnderſtanding he is obliged to do? For not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging any authority of Church, or Prelats indued with infallibility, he is ſtill left to his owne reaſon. Beſides one effect of excommunication is to exclude the Perſon ſo cenſured, from the ciuill conuerſation with others; other temporall puniſhments in all Courts being alſo conſequent to it. Seeing then he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes that men are to be puniſhed for their opinions by Temporall puniſhments, he cannot with cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence affirme, that they may lawfully be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated: This certainly being a greater enforcement then death it ſelfe, to ſuch as vnderſtand the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all benefits, and aduantages, of which men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued by that Cenſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> By that which hath been ſaid in theſe few prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chapters it euidently appeares; first, how fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it was for the good of our Country in theſe preſent circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>stances, that people ſhould haue learned by ſome ſuch Treatiſe as the <hi>Direction,</hi> to beware of impious <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> ſuch as were foreſeene that this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would vent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of defending the Protestant cauſe, and anſwering <hi>Charity maintayned.</hi> And that although nothing could
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2349:44"/>be intended more diſgracefull to Protestant Religion, then to ſee a Champion, &amp; a way choſen to defend it, which open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly destroyes all Religion; yet Compaſsion could not but worke in a wel-wiſhing ſoule, and mooue it to deſire, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that ſuch a way ſhould not be taken, which might make people more and more inſenſible of any Religion, by blurring the common principles of Christianity, and digging vp the foundation thereof, to lay inſteed of them, the grounds of Atheiſme.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Secondly though this hath not taken the full effect which could haue been wished, &amp; that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the warning giuen, he hath interlac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his whole booke with ſuch stuffe as here you haue ſeene; yet this we haue gotten further, that it is diſcouered cleerly to the world, how deeply <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> is rooted in this man, (and, as it is to be feared, in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with whome he muſt needes haue had much conference ſince his vndertaking the worke) in regard that no timely aduiſe or <hi>Direction,</hi> no force of reaſon, no feare of ſhame or puniſhment, no former impreſsions of Chriſtianity could withdraw him from steeping his thoughts and pen in ſuch vn-Christian inke; nor the many Corrections endeauoured by the Approouers of his Booke, blot out his errours, though in reſpect of the alterations which haue been by report made in it by them, it is quite another thing from the first plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme which he drew, and put into their hands; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently how iust reaſon the <hi>Directour</hi> had to ſuſpect, that his <hi>true intention,</hi> was not to <hi>defend Proteſtantiſme,</hi> but couertly <hi>to vent Socinianiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Now, thirdly, whether it be not high time that people ſhould now at the least open their eyes vpon this ſecond war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and take that order which may be conuenient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the ſpreading of ſo pernicious a Sect, I must leaue to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2349:45"/>the conſideration of euery one whome it may concerne. I do only for the preſent wiſh from my hart, that the maintayning of that Bleſsed Title, and State of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> of which our Countrey hath been for ſo many ages poſseſſed, may be the effect both of this mans wauering and wandering tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, and of theſe my labours.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PRaeſat. pag. 10. lin. 25. <hi>to our nation</hi> corrige <hi>of our nation</hi> Ibid. pag. <hi>11.</hi> lin. 26. <hi>with</hi> corrige <hi>with</hi> Pag. 32. lin. 3. is the <hi>corrige</hi> is ſo Ibid. lin. 4. by ſo <hi>corrige</hi> by the Pag. 53. lin. 21. Chriſt is God, <hi>lege,</hi> is the Sonne of God</p>
            <p>In the margent <hi>pag.</hi> 11. ouer againſt S. Bernard eited <hi>line</hi> 3. put. <hi>Bernard. Epist.</hi> 87.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2349:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
